You are listening to ancient faith radio, Orthodox Christianity for today's world.
He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall, and
he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him.
And they will...
praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels, demons,
and saints. In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism,
to see and to know reality as it truly is. What is this spiritual reality like? How do we engage with
it well. How do we...
permeate everyday life with spiritual presence.
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick
and Father Stephen DeYoung, host this live Colin show,
focused on enchantment in creation,
the union of the scene and unseen as made by God
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Christ is risen.
Good evening, you giant killers, dragon slayers,
gougers of gangrenous golems.
You are listening to the Lord of...
this is episode 116.
My co-host, Father Stephen D. Young, the Quixotic Questing Beasts of the Quix Stand
is with me straight from the swamp in Lafayette, Louisiana.
I'm Father Andrew Stephen Dayman,
and I'm a Pennsylvania Perch precariously atop the arcane tower of podcasting,
hovering dozens, dozens as it were of stories above a disused gateway to the underworld.
And we are live.
And if you're listening to us live, you can call us at 855-237-2346.
237 2346 and you can talk to us and we'll get your call.
in the second half of the show and to Mike flash in the pan again, we'll be taking your calls.
If you can figure out how to press all the buttons and turn all the knobs and push all the faders.
Also, if you're also if you're listening to us live, I really feel like we need a soundboard
on the show just so where we have a lead in like the one we just had we can drop you know and
now for something completely different. Oh yes, you know I have at home you know some
one when I was out and about on one of my speaking
engagements, someone gave me a goat, like a little toy goat
that when you press it makes a screaming goat sound. And
that I think would be fantastic for this show. I don't
know if it would have the same effect that I'm going for
though. I'm just I'm trying to avoid our listeners getting
whiplash. There's kind of a lot of feminine energy going on
there. And then wow, with the screaming goat or and then
all of a sudden no, no, no, no, no, the previous show and
Now us right like oh
previous show. Yes. Yeah. That's what I was saying. Right. We need we need some kind of segue.
I mean, it sounded I mean, yeah, we were told, you know, make sure you get a good therapist.
I mean, that's probably good advice for a lot of people. But this is not your therapy. Everybody,
this is no. This is why you go to therapy. Yes. Right. I have said several people to therapy.
I'm pretty sure. Of course, with my life, teachers, vice principals. But you know, if you're not
checked into rehab or therapy or whatever.
that is the first week in an October for the Laura Spirits Conference of the Antioch in
Village. We have sold out all the rooms at the village, but there are lots of commuter
tickets available. So you can get a room somewhere else nearby and drive in. You may not, you
may not, as some people apparently attempted, I don't know, or at least we heard that they
are going to attempt to, you may not camp out in the parking lot. That is not okay.
There's a lot of open land around there man.
I think you could there are places you could squat. That's all I'm saying. There's a
I. That part of the lady that's probably a lot of abandoned buildings. That is probably true.
That is so. So anyway, if you do find a place to rest your your weary head, you can go to
store. I'd ancient feet.com slash events and and get your ticket. So it's going to be a lot of
I've already seen, I'll say this, I've seen Father Stevens title.
and his blurb for the talk he's going to give.
And the title is longer than the blurb.
Yeah, part of that too, you should know is, I have no idea
what I'm going to talk about yet.
I just wrote something.
See, I know.
Yes, I got your number when I when I filled out the form.
So I know.
I think I now have an idea what I'm going to talk about.
But that may change between trying to make Ellie's life hard.
Ellie, one of the most company human beings
in the known universe to run.
That's right, not to make her life hard.
I was trying to send her the form in a timely fashion very good.
In order to do that, I had to just, you know, go with something.
I'd fill in that blank.
It was required.
It was required field.
The little red thing appeared required field.
Yep.
Required field with a little asterisk, the little red bits.
Yes.
So since I had to put something tonight, tonight, everyone,
we are going to conclude our three part series on the history of Israel.
And our first part we followed Israel from its prehistory in Abraham
to its birth in the Exodus.
to the giving of the Torah, and in the second part, we covered the formation of Israel as a kingdom,
including some Gigantomaki. Everyone was very excited. And then the break up into two kingdoms,
Israel and Judah, and finally its dissolution in the exiles. So with this final chapter then,
we begin with Judah and the Babylonian exile, singing the songs of Zion in a strange land.
So what happens next? I don't know because the Old Testament kind of ends there.
That's right. There's four hundred silent years. Were you raised with that idea?
I mean, you raised us for four, but they did they had this idea of 400 silent years
between Malachi and Matthew basically. I was never really taught that
But the time anybody got into it. It was always for the perspective of here's why those Catholic books aren't in the Bible, right?
Right, right?
There was never sort of
just a neutral like, oh, hey, there's just this period of time between the testaments.
It was more polemical than that, shall we?
Yeah.
Not, you know, Dutch people are more prognatious than average or anything.
Right.
So we, we, let's pause there for a second because I like there is a beautiful irony there.
Okay.
Right.
I mean actual irony not
a lot of us more set irony. Thank you.
In that,
the when they say, well, why are you saying there's 400 silent years?
Why are you saying that there's no,
those scripts are written during this time?
And you get this quote from first Macabees that in those days,
there was no profit in the land.
Yes, it will see.
There's a famine of prophecy in the land.
And so there's no scripture writing.
And I'm like, but you.
just quoted first Macabees.
Has to it were scripture as though we're true. Yeah.
The authoritative.
Check. Oh, yeah.
It's interesting.
But yeah, so yeah, that's not a.
That's not really a thing. Right.
So obviously the history regardless your perspective
on the canon of scripture without going down
that rabbit hole too far.
Obviously, the history of Israel continued, right?
Things happened between the end of the book of Nehomaya
and the beginning of the New Testament.
Yeah.
And that's pretty obvious when you start reading
the New Testament and all of a sudden
there are all these Pharisees and Sadducees and Synagogues
and, right?
Which just seems just sprung up out of nowhere apparently.
Yeah, and all these Jewish people with names
that you don't recognize from the old test of it.
right? If you don't know anything about that, you're going to find out about that tonight.
Stay tuned. Settle in everybody. Yeah. So there would be this one. Yeah. This episode is going to be.
So the last couple episodes we're talking about stuff that we've talked about before,
that lots of people have talked about before, but we were kind of coming at it from another angle and ruining your Sunday school.
Right. Tonight's episode.
going to be a lot more just, hey, here's some information you probably don't know and have
never heard.
There's going to be sort of a lot more of that as we sort of fill in some of this history.
A lot of narrative this time around.
Yeah.
And we're going to go through a whole dynasty of kings.
So when last time on Lord of Spirits.
We play it. It was a sweep through the plate.
the flashback montage. Yeah. At the end of our last episode, right? As
Father Edder mentioned, we left off with right, Judah going into exile, a
Syria having wiped out the northern kingdom of Israel. And people, we
talked about what the expectation was, right? How, how were the people
understanding
that the greater promises to Abraham, of which the land had been assigned.
But sort of the greater, larger promises of Abraham would finally be,
would finally be fulfilled, right?
What were they expecting to happen?
What were they expecting to change?
Where were they expecting to come?
And to just kind of summarize that, summarize the point,
this is basically the same summary as we ended with last time, right?
that God was going to act decisively in history.
to establish the order that's described in the Torah.
Remember the Torah was given as an ought.
That was who Israel was supposed to be.
That's never who they actually were.
They never lived up to it.
That's why the destruction of the Northern Kingdom
and the exile of Judah happened.
But now God is going to take action to make that real.
And he's going to take that action through a Messiah, right?
through a Messianic king, a king after the pattern, after the type of David, right?
And who is a descendant of David?
And he is going to that intervention through the Messianic King is going to establish his kingdom.
It's going to establish justice, the justice described in the Torah.
It's going to restore Israel, both the Northern and Southern kingdoms, and we'll get into that more
as we go on
tonight and free the people from the curse of the Torah. Remember the curse that's literally
the curses and unceded in the Torah for not having kept it. Yeah, right. Under which the
people were languishing in exile. Okay, so this is this is what they're hoping for. This
is what they're expecting to come. And now we begin tonight. Tonight.
the heroine conclusion.
Um, we're going to, sorry, what, okay, so what actually happens now?
This is their expectation.
How does history sort of unfold?
So Judah had been taking it.
We talked more about the Assyrians last time, but Judah had been taking it exile by actually
the neo-Babalonean empire.
We just referred to Babylon, but remember they're the neo-Babalonean empire.
the New Babylonian Empire in the 6th century BC.
because the the experience took the northern part.
Right. Right. Yeah. And the original Babylonian Empire, this is
Hamir Abbi and the Umuru, this is back in the Bronze Age. Right.
That fell apart of the Bronze Age collapse. So this is the neo-Babalone
Empire, which is begun by Nabbo Palacir.
Babylon becomes ascended again. It begins to take action.
toward conquering Nineveh, the Syrian empire, and then going from there. But all of this
really comes to fruition, and the empire is established by Nabbo Palassar's son, Nebuchadnezzar,
AKA Nebuchadrezzar, AKA Nebuchaduru, Kudur, Kubbidinnozor. Yeah. I feel like the great
for a young, easy, oh no, wait, no, that's not real.
Adding syllables. Yeah.
In, in Veggie Teal.
It's a treasure, it's I recall.
I think go nether.
Nether, that's more accurate.
Nether, Nether Naboo Kadooroo Utsur, which means something like holy soul of Naboo,
Naboo being one of the Babylonian gods.
Yeah.
Good to be of work, Dave.
Not just a planet with gungans.
Anyway.
So, um,
he's really right.
And he of course becomes a major figure in scripture.
because of his error.
actions with God, right? And we talked about that more, go back to our episode on Mad Men,
not the John Ham show, but yeah, actual men who have gone mad, among whom was Nibbukhidesar.
We talked more about that. But the Neobabalonean Empire, as glorious as it may have been,
not last very long.
This is another one of those time frame things.
We talked about the relatively small period of time
that Israel and Judah existed in the world.
The neo-Babalonean empire, who's around for a bad essentially,
that was about it.
We'll talk more about who came next in a minute.
But we tend to, so we have in our heads
that what happened to the Northern Kingdom
what happened to the sun.
other kingdom are sort of fundamentally different things, right? Yeah.
Cause the northern kingdom was wiped out. And Judah just went into exile. Okay.
But we're looking at that with hindsight. Right. Yeah.
Through the leads of the scriptures. What actually happened, of course, was the
Assyrians sure mass occurred a lot of people, right? But they did kill
literally everybody. They slaughtered
massacre to a whole lot of people, but then they took a big group of those people to Assyria
and relocated them, right, in particular villages. And over the course of about a century,
we see in the Assyrian records the Hebrew names disappear, right? So they just intermarry
and dissolve culturally into Assyria, which was the goal. That was the purpose for relocating
them and as we talked about last time other people were relocated to.
Samaria and the area around it, right?
Samaria having been the capital of the Northern Kingdom.
They're going to become the Samaritans, more about the Samaritans tonight also.
And so there was this force relocation essentially an exile, right?
And so don't be confused.
Never could nester at the time he takes, I mean he killed a whole lot of people in Judah.
Yeah.
And when he took those people to Babylon into exile, he was planning at least at that point.
Now he repented of things later, right?
We know, but he also died and was replaced by another Babylonian emperor who was not so keen.
He was not intending to send them back at some point.
Yeah, there was no sense of like, oh, God has told me to take these people into exile for
their testisement for 70 years.
And then said them back, right?
the new Babylon Empire never sends them back. Okay.
Yeah, the next people. It doesn't last. So they were planning on doing the exact same thing that
the Assyrians did to the Northern Kingdom from the Babylonian side. Now God didn't let that happen
in the case of Judah. So the difference is God intervenes to for the sake as the scriptures say
over and over again of his servant David, God intervenes to make the exile a temporary thing.
and that intervention happens through.
the aforementioned next guy who is Cyrus the Great, the first emperor of the Persian Empire,
to be more specific, the Accomended Empire, because there are other Persian empires later in history.
The main one you hear about being the Sassanid Empire. But
so the
The Cyrus comes from Persis, which is where Persia gets its name.
which was actually a little province in what's now Southern Iran in the middle of the Northern
coast of the Persian Gulf. You could look up a map of the interwebs, the Googles,
and you will see that I'm correct. But I would say or just pull out the atlas of the
the nearest that everyone has under their bed.
What you should.
So.
But Cyrus manages to unite the people of Persis and get them on the road to conquest.
And that involves not just obviously you say, well, how could, that seems like a rather small
group of people.
How could you conquer that much territory?
He doesn't just, he does not operate according to the kind of principles the Assyrians or even
the Babylonians used.
he's great at making deals.
Oh, so he goes to the tribes of the Meads, right, and these other people groups surrounding
him and unites them under his rule.
Right.
So he is not just a sort of conqueror.
He is also a coalition builder.
I see.
I mean, is he is he paying them off or is he saying we can go to fortune and glory if you
all kinds of things like that?
Marriages.
like
all of a down the line. Like he's good at this. Right. So Cyrus, the great is very different
than a lot of these other figures that we've already talked about and that we're going to
talk about next time like or later on tonight, like Alexander the Great, right? In that
he's not great in the same way. Yeah. He's a great general, right? He does win a lot of battles.
Right. Yeah. Right. Defeat the Babylon Empire, for example, eventually. But
but what he's
But he's very good at is this kind of coalition building and building infrastructure.
So the the first Persian Empire here is more like the Roman Empire in that regard.
One of the things that facilitates is he's very good, very good at administration.
He creates a massive bureaucratic state.
He standardizes what's called imperial air amic.
language that we think of as Aramaic, that parts of the Hebrew Bible are actually
it and then like big chunks of Daniel and Ezra. That Aramaic is Imperial Aramaic. That is
the standardized language of the Persian Empire. Yeah. And spreads that Aramaic over a vast swath
of the world. Right. His successor, Jarius, if you're fancy or dareous, if you're not.
or a hoody fan.
It kind of takes the empire to, well, we mostly, it's Apigee, and at its height, right,
the Accompanied Empire controls like Egypt and Northern Libya controls.
Doesn't get Greece.
The Ghosts for Greece doesn't get Greece.
It's Persian Wars, we know about that.
But gets Thraces up above Greece.
So into Eastern Europe, all the way across a big chunk of what was then part of India that's
now.
modern Pakistan all the way over to there, Afghanistan, right, all of what's Iran, Iraq,
the Arabian Peninsula, right, this vast swath of territory, and actually is able to administer
it very successfully. Yeah, it's one thing to take out rulers and subject the peoples and whatever,
but it's something else entirely to actually run the place.
Yeah.
And the Persians are going to...
be the reason why there are these groups in Eastern Europe and or other
Baltic who use Aramaic for centuries thereafter. Yeah, right.
They're spreading that language around an Aramaic over into like I said
Pakistan India over in that direction. So
The characters' character here becomes very important.
So Cyrus takes a very different approach to the people under his rule, whether conquered
or bargained for or treated with or however they ended up part of the Persian Empire.
Famously he would send emissaries, right? This is the whole scene in 300 which obviously is not
not a super realistic portrayal, but what?
What?
Some of the basic facts.
are correct in that he would send emissaries, right, with salt and with things. And the
emissaries would basically he would just call on these to submit to the Persian Empire and
explain here are all the good things, right? They will come to you if you become part of
this empire because he really did have things to offer.
Yes, sure.
In terms of infrastructure, wealth, trade, right? All kind, I mean, he had all these things
to offer whatever the presions have done.
us. And yeah, he would he would offer the King's positions as heads of satraps of provinces
and stuff, right? He didn't just he wasn't like kill them all, right? And make a show of
it like the experience. It was, you know, you could have this exalted position. You're
still going to govern your territory. You're just going to be governing under me, right?
Yeah, so it was he always tried that first now gotta be fair also
just he not just Cyrus but his successors even Circus and so Ardor's
Ericsies who's a swear spain. They they always try that first. Now, but we have to
be fair, if you said no, they would then come and conquer you, right? Then they
said to the military, right, and take it by force. And then the king gets his head
chopped off and then right things go bad. But this is the whole seated 300 where
the guy comes to give these terms to
Sparta, right?
You know, here's all the Guzial Serenity gets kicked down the well, right?
Like the famous scene.
Yeah. So the Greeks kind of started that, but on the other hand,
they were kind of being extorted at the same time.
But even that gives you a view that Cyrus and his successors had a different,
Had a different maybe and maybe even we might say more practical.
approach to expanding and governing their empire. Right? It wasn't about
conquest and defeat and grinding people's faces into the ground like the
Assyrians. And they didn't and Cyrus didn't feel the need to sort of
expunge all of the different people groups. Right? As long as they submitted
his authority, that was fine. Yeah, he was he was cool with the coalition. Yeah,
It's kind of like the papacy.
No.
But, uh.
See you soon.
Steven. Yeah. As long as he comes in his authority, he'll let you do your thing, right?
Um, tough stuff. So, um, and so he takes this, this approach really with the, the Jewish
exiles right that Judahite exiles who he has and traditionally this happens in part.
They come and appeal to him, right, and make it appeal to him.
Because he had, by that point, acquired the territory that had been Judah, right.
So it's still part of his empire, right.
And came and presented to him, we're not repelling against you.
We're not trying to leave your empire.
We want to remain your subjects.
We just want to go back and live where we came from, right.
and be your happy, obedient subjects there.
Instead of here.
Right, and we just want to we'll be over there in the corner. We want to you know practice our way of life
religiously and everything right but we're not going to be any bother to you right will offer sacrifices on your behalf to our God
Right, we'll do all these I say right
And traditionally also showed him some passages in the Hebrew Scriptures that referred to him
possibly even by day.
We're already written at that point to sort of get on his good side, right?
Of, you know, our God has chosen you to be the one who returns us, right?
To our land. And Cyrus does it.
Right. Cyrus does it.
He allows permits.
Those verbs are important.
the judoied exiles who want to.
to return to the land that had been Judah.
This, he allows that to happen.
Now, the reason I keep saying allows permits is not everyone who's going to go back there.
Yeah.
Right.
A lot of people probably like, look, this is where I live now.
For generations we've lived here.
Yeah.
I have a life here.
I have a job.
I have a house.
You know, my kids are here.
And the most significant, I mean, it was 70 years, right?
So you've got as a couple generations of people,
there are people who have been born and lived their whole life
somewhere else.
Yeah, right.
You have never lived in Judah.
And so the big significant groups in that category,
right, are first, when you read Jeremiah,
there's a large group of Judahites centered around Jerusalem,
a lot of them the wealthier folks,
who sort of...
believed Jeremiah's prophesying and saw the writing on the wall that Jerusalem was going to fall
to the Babylonians and made plans to go to Egypt. Glad to move to Egypt. Jeremiah did not want them to
do that. They wanted him to come to, he refused to do that. They shanghaied him. That's why super
politically correct now to say. I'm going to say, now I already said it. So they shanghaied him and
took him to...
took him to Egypt anyway. And those folks settled in an area called Leontopolis, which was sort of in our modern terms a suburb of Alexandria.
And the central area of Lee and Toppillus is still called Tell Yehudi.
Wow, really?
Egypt to this day.
the Hill of the Jews. Yeah, yeah. And so there was this large community there and in those
70 years they had set down roots and continued to set down roots. And so Alexandria and Judaism
as a particular form of Judaism comes into being there. Philo of Alexandria will later
be a famous example of Alexandria and Judaism.
Yeah.
And at the time, of course, it isn't Alexandria.
because Alexander hasn't come through yet. But that's right. Yeah. Yeah. But they're just
in this area. Right. That's going to be Lee and Toppillus. And eventually down the road, it's a
while down the road from this. It's a couple hundred years after the exile. But they're eventually
going to take over a temple of bast.
what's the best?
Hmm.
Oh, which God or Goddess is that?
Which cat?
That cat head.
Yes, yes, it was also the God they worship in Wakanda.
How about that?
Anyway, so, but yeah, so vast, who's this cat God, there was a disused temple of vast,
it was actually an obelisk in shape that they took over and turned into a Jewish temple.
And that Jewish
Papalisk temple in Leontopolis was there until you hoody until AD 73
Meaning there were three years after the destruction of the temple of Jerusalem where that was the only Jewish temple in the world
Yeah, and the reason it was destroyed was that Rome told the governor to tear it down because
The temple of Jerusalem had become this hub for rebellion. He didn't want the same thing to happen in Egypt. Yeah
Yeah.
And for the record, that was not a temple. The way they viewed that temple, it's kind of interesting.
They did not think it was another temple like the one in Jerusalem.
They used the Psalm verse about God having an altar of incense in Egypt to justify it.
But they saw it as sort of a satellite temple.
Huh, like it wasn't the real temple, but it was sort of like an embassy or an extension of the temple in Jerusalem.
So they would send their tithes and offerings to the temple in Jerusalem and make pilgrimage there when they could from Alexandria.
But for sort of day to day stuff, they would go to this one in Leontopoulos, as if it was sort of an outpost.
So it's kind of an interesting dynamic in the house of the ingenious of this kind of view.
the idea that like you're only supposed to actually do sacrifices in Jerusalem.
But there's this portal to Egypt.
Well, yeah, well, and I mean, keep in mind, right?
Like we're saying that, yes, the Torah is super clear.
You're only supposed to offer sacrifices in Jerusalem.
But the Northern Kingdom had been offering sacrifices
all over the place, Bethel and it's whole existence, right?
So it's not like this is some radical thing
different than anything any, you know, Israelite
or Jewish person had ever considered.
I mean, it's, it's Luke.
great in terms of yes, right? Right. Right. At least there's no golden calf there. Right.
Like there's no, you know, right. Could be way, way worse. So so Alexandria, Judy is it because
of the thing because a lot of them stay. Right. The other major group like significant group coming
out of this is there are a whole lot of people who
of of Judah exiles who stay in Mesopotamia. Yeah. And lay the roots for what becomes Babylonian,
what do I call Babylonian Judaism? There's a reason why the Babylonian Tellment is called the Babylonian
Tellment. Yeah. So there are these, there's a significant Jewish community, right? Still about
in that part of the Persian Empire that just remains where they are. Yeah. I mean, you see the books
some Daniel and
Yes, exactly. I mean, I was going to say, and even to this day, there are communities of Jews that live in various parts of the Middle East, who they trace their, they trace their roots back to like this period.
Yeah, that's the bottom line.
like that's not weird claim that's legit.
And then of course, you also get people settling in...
parts of the Levant that weren't technically part of Judah before, right?
So you get people who come back and settle in around the Sea of Galilee and stuff that
had belonged to other tribes in the Northern Kingdom and that kind of thing.
Because that freedom to return to Judea also included they had kind of freedom to travel
within the Persian Empire.
So you get small groups of Judah, right?
sounds would go in the various places.
Right.
within the Persian Empire for various reasons, you know, having to do with work and trade,
commerce and all kinds of things. Maybe, you know, whether the arthritis was acting, I don't know.
So, so, you do however have this significant group that goes back to what had Ben Judah.
And when they get there,
They set about rebuilding the temple and the city.
The Hamaya, of course, there's everything about rebuilding the city wall around Jerusalem
because even though this is all Persian Empire now, there's all kinds of people groups and
nomadic tribes and all kinds of people living around in that area now, right?
And the so the defense of the returning
Judite exiles was important and of course rededicating the temple
And so they do rededicate the temple that temple is the second temple after which this period is named
Yes, that could temple period
And but when they rebuild that temple and they rededicate it
If something doesn't happen
Right
The stories that we read in Leviticus about the tabernacle
and in first kings and I think it's at the end of first chronicles about the dedication that might be beginning of second chronicles about the dedication of the temple.
Those where there's this the theophatic glory cloud appears and fills the tabernacle or fills the temple, the glory of the Lord, and there's this visible theophany right there's this visual visual manifestation of God.
God.
and his presence there, that doesn't happen when they dedicate the second temple.
Which I mean, that must have been pretty disappointing.
You know, like, wait, is this real?
Is our, is God so mad?
You know, right, and cue all the possible things.
Did we do it wrong?
Right.
Did we need to, did we say where we should have zagged?
Right? Did we say the wrong words?
Did we use the wrong recipe for anointing oil?
right? Or insides. But I mean, ultimately the people soldier on, but this creates this tension.
Right? So the Hebrew scriptures themselves refer to Cyrus as the Messiah.
Yeah, right. Right. And we talked about, go back and listen to our Messiah episode.
In this period, they didn't necessarily think there was only going to be one Messiah.
Yes, yes, right. The Messiah bend. They've decided to
of David, right, is the one we're usually talking about, but there were other ideas about
other Messiahs and Messianic figures going around. But you can see, right, so in a certain
sense, okay, we're, we, we, the X-House kind of over because a lot of us are back here in
the land. And we've got the Temple back and this king, this great king, you know, over
the known world.
as intervened on our behalf, right?
And God was working through him to do this.
And this is kind of the kind of stuff
we were expecting to happen, but very incomplete.
Yeah.
Like kind of Messiah-ish, kind of stuff.
Like this is the beginning of something.
Right.
But not really the fulfillment, right?
Not the end, right?
like there's...
There's more here to do, right?
That hasn't happened yet.
But so all of these communities then sort of soldier on, right?
So as best they can, they restore the priesthood, they begin offering the sacrifices again,
they begin celebrating the feasts again in Judea, right?
And then the the the Judahites who are living in these
other places will make pilgrimage to the temple, but they remain living where they're living.
And so some important ideas develop here, right here at the end of the exile, that are
critically important going forward in history.
There are some things that change in some terms, right?
Because what ends up happening is those returning judaid exiles form this province of Judea.
Yeah.
There's going to be a province of other people's empires later on.
Right.
I think sometimes people get the impression maybe that, you know, that the Persians or
the Babylonians or whoever, a conquered Judea and then walk away with their people and their
stuff and it's just sort of left abandoned.
And then when the Israelites, you know, when they get to go back home, oh, we've got our
own independent country again, you know, like we're Israel again.
But but no, it's no you are allowed to move back into this region that is still conquered occupied land
Right
And so now the Greek terms are a little later not much later. We're gonna get to the Greeks here in the second half but yeah
The Greek terms for these ideas we get the idea of you day, right, which is the plural
Which literally means Judeans
Yeah, people from that spot, right?
the people of Judea, the people of that province, right?
Those people.
And that word often gets translated
like in English New Testaments as Jews.
Yeah, which, I mean, just a shortening of Judeans.
Yeah, I mean, it's a pretty straightforward
etymological tour from that to, yeah.
Although interestingly, I looked up,
see, and now all these people are gonna be mad
that I don't have the jingle ready to go,
because it just occurred to me.
But I looked up.
like what was what was the term in Old English because Jew ultimately comes through
French to middle English to modern English. But so Old English, of course obviously had a term
for this because they had the Bible and it was something like Yudesh, something like that. So
you know, Judah-ish people. Yeah. So like to the eye, right? Yeah, right. Yeah, right. Yeah, exactly.
Yeah. But.
Then there is also this idea of Udayi's most.
Yeah, Judaism, which gets translated as Judaism.
Yes.
And the word Udayi, right, that as we've said,
kinda means Judeans,
can't get used in two different ways.
or does get used in two different ways, right? In subsequent history.
So sometimes, as we said, it's used to mean the people of Judea, that's straightforward meaning.
Right? But sometimes it's used to mean someone who practices Udaiz Mos.
Yeah, so the people who live the way that those people do.
Right.
Right. The people who follow the no-mose of Judea. Right. So there is a Judean way of life.
Right. And way of life, I think, is the best way of describing it. This of course is the Torah.
This is the way of life set out by the Torah. The Torah is the no-mose of
of the Jewish people, the Judean people. That's why no-mose is used to translate Torah in the New
testament. And way of life includes everything.
Yeah, and I mean correct me if I'm wrong on this, but my my sense is that
That that phenomenon of this group of people who live in this way and yet aren't on their land
That that probably would have been kind of weird to most pagans right where there's a sense of
This God rules over this area. So since you're here you should worship that God because they're the one in charge here
Well, or at least incorporate it
Yeah.
Right. Like if you're from Thrace, right? And you're now living in, you know,
Frigia, right?
You would worship both, you know, the gods of your family and your ancestors from Thrace,
and the gods of Frigia. Yeah. Right. Like you would, you would just sort of incorporate those things.
Yeah.
Because I remember everybody like we tend to think of this in terms of what we call religion
But but to ancient peoples
gods are spiritual rulers
They are powers that are in your place
You know, so it's not oh these are my private convictions. This is what I think what I feel whatever
You know, it's like like imagine you're an ex-patriot. You know an ex-pat you go live in some other country
You
Okay, you're still a citizen of the United States wherever.
So you might do things like vote,
and have that connection with your home country,
but you also have to deal with the authorities
in the place that you live, right?
So that's much more like the way
that what we think of as religion
worked in the ancient world.
And so then this people that basically say,
we have this citizenship, so to speak,
that follows us wherever we go, and no other,
that's a little weird for the people.
Right, in this sense.
that you would not find, right? Like you wouldn't find someone who, uh, yeah, three generations
ago his family lived in Athens. Yeah. For the last three generations, you know, they've
lived in, they've lived in Ephesus, but he refuses to celebrate any of the festivals of Ephesus
or worship any of the gods of Ephesus. He only worships the Athenian gods and he celebrates
the festivals of Athens like by himself with his family at home.
Alright.
That's not a thing. That's not a thing that happened. Right. Yeah. Yeah. Right. Um, but
it's going to a thiena and have acedus, but super into Artemis now as well. Right.
And of course, the Torah includes everything. It is all encompassing. Yeah. Right. You
can't just boil it down to culture or religion or any of these disparate things, right?
The Torah covers how you dress, what you eat, where you go and don't go when you do it.
Right? Is it?
Right? Like who you worship, how you worship who you worship everything, right?
so
Keeping Torah no matter where you are, right following that nomus following the Judean way of life, right?
Which is why they would just refer to you as a Judean
Right, you're still a Judean. You're not really an Athenian even though you lived and lived in Athens for three generations
You're not really an Athenian
You're still a Judean right because you're practicing
you die as well. So you're practicing the Judean way of life still. You're living the Judean way of life.
And so the fact that you have all these people and you don't have any kind of transit where these folks can
unless they're just obscenely wealthy somehow can go to Jerusalem for every single feast,
while living somewhere very distant, right? You also can't really
Keep Torah fully all by yourself.
Yeah, it requires a group.
Yes, it requires a community, right?
Yeah, even today I think, is it the case?
I don't know how this rule is, but don't you have to have 12 Jewish men to have?
I think you just have to have three.
Three?
Okay, I think you just have to have three adult Jewish men.
Yeah.
But, and I think it's kind of presumed that that then includes their families, right?
Thank you.
The Internet says 10 but who knows if that's good.
Well, it may differ in different.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, groups, too.
But anyway, and so this is what gives birth to synagogues.
You're not going to see anything about synagogues in the Torah.
No, it doesn't say that that's a thing.
Or anything about synagogues in the rest of the Hebrew Bible.
It's the community center.
the place where you have the scriptures where you
place where you gather. And if they're not temples, you don't go there and offer sacrifice,
no, like a temple. It's teaching, it's reading the scriptures, it's prayer, observing the
feasts as you can in that place away from the temple. But see that as you can means that
once the synagogues start to be established, you start to develop those as you can. So we
can't do the whole thing with the two goats on the day of atonement, right? We're not at
the temple.
So, what do we do on the day of atonement in Athens or Alexandria?
Yeah, right.
Well, we're going to gather together as Jewish people and we're going to pray the prayers
and we're going to read right about the day of atonement.
We're going to repent of our sins, right?
That's when these things start developing.
It reminds me in some ways of, I mean, I don't know a huge amount about this, but a little
bit about the, what they call the pre-slessed old believers from, from Russia Orthodox history.
well they still exist that you know
they believe that God takes away the priesthood from the world because of sin and the end of
the world is coming and so forth.
And yet they continue to do church services without priests.
So it's essentially a series of reader services.
But then they still have to do things like baptized people and Mary people.
And so they kind of develop ways of doing that that sort of still acknowledged that the priesthood
is missing.
And yet, well, life goes on.
Life goes on.
Thank you.
Yeah, and so but but this is important historically because over the next few centuries
Right, you have a large number of Jewish people all over the world
Who still are connected in various ways spiritual
Right emotional ancestral to Jerusalem in the temple right and would all tell you Jerusalem is the temple
That is the place where God it right they would not deny any of those things yeah
But on a track.
their day-to-day observance of the Torah.
They're gathering for worship, right?
Their actual experience of it is very disconnected from the temple, right?
Because they're not physically there, right?
And, and therefore, also, right, functionally, we go from how can we sing the songs of Zion in a foreign land to...
we're going to practice the Torre.
foreign land. Yeah, because you got to live. Which means their develops a disconnect over time
right in the sense that the land itself and the temple itself loses the kind of
ultimacy that it had during the kingdom period that we talked about in the last episode.
Right. The the fact that those were not the ultimate, that those were assigned, that those were
pointing
something greater, right, becomes more clear during this period of the synagogue in Second
Temple Judaism. And it allows a segment admittedly, and we're going to talk more about the
Pharisees in the next half. But it allows at least a significant segment of Jewish people
to become effectively prepared for the temple to go away.
And for returning to the land, not even being an option really anymore under the Romans,
right?
That's going to happen.
And horrible things are going to happen related to it, but there are going to be people who are prepared sort of for it to happen and to go on because they already know how to go on.
They've already developed the synagogues and the things that they need to continue to observe the cycle of feasts and things without a temple.
those things sort of will have happened, right? But that also, at the same time, as we said,
because that sort of breaks a tether to the past, right? This is why when we talk about religion and
we've used this language through the whole history of this show, you have ancient Israelite religion,
and you have second temple Judaism
and then you have rabbinic Judaism, right?
Ancient Israelite religion and second-table Judaism are not the same and this is what we're talking about right now are some of the big significant changes.
Right because there weren't a ton of Judahites living outside Judah before the exile.
Yeah just yeah it wasn't thinkable it was not.
Right like that wasn't a thing God brought them to the land that was all of it but as we said that was always pointing forward to something else.
And so this breaking of connections is
practical breaking of connections to the past, right?
Helps reorient these Jewish communities, not just the ones outside Judea, but all of them
ultimately helps reorient them more toward the future.
So it's not anymore for a lot of them.
Again, we're going to talk more about the Pharisees.
It's not about we need to get back what we had before the exile.
It's we're
looking forward still to God intervening in history
and something different coming.
Yeah, I mean, and like two things that occur to me is,
you know, like it so alters the way that Judaism works
that even in Judea you get synagogues by the time,
you know, that gets to the New Testament
or synagogues and the Indians.
And now that's something that aren't that far away.
Even though there's a temple sitting right there.
Yeah.
But and then also like, I mean, so much of this forms
the backdrop of the conversation that we just,
that we just heard and ch-
church on Sunday of Christ speaking to the Samaritan woman.
Right. You know, like where do you worship all of that?
And we'll get into the Samaritan's a little more here in the second half.
Yeah. Yeah.
And what's been going on with them and their parallel development.
Um, yeah.
Yeah.
All right.
Well, that's the first half of this episode of Lord of Spience.
We right back after this break.
Father Andrew Stephen, David and Father Stephen, DeYoung will be back in a moment.
Take your calls on the next part of the...
of spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF radio.
The centuries after the Protestant Reformation brought about a radical reinterpretation of the
epistles of St. Paul, disconnected from any historical reality. The Paul operated
during his entire life as a faithful Pharisee within the wrong
in Jewish world. In St. Paul the Pharisee, Jewish Apostle to all nations, Father Stephen
D. Young surveys Paul's life in writings, interpreting them within the holy tradition of the Orthodox
Church. This survey is followed by D. Young's interpretive translation of St. Paul's Epistles,
which deliberately avoids overly familiar terminology. By using words and ideas grounded in
first century Judaism.
DeYoung hopes to unsettle commonly held notions and help the reader read-
He assessed Saint Paul in his historical context.
Hey, welcome back.
is the second half of the third part of our series on the history of Israel. And I don't
know, did you say something really controversial, Father, because suddenly we're getting all
these phone calls that are coming in. You're really everything I say is controversial.
Walking controversy machine. Keeping it hot. All right. Well, we're going to take some vinegar.
Thank you.
We're going to go ahead and take our first call.
So we have David calling from Tennessee.
David, welcome, Lord of Spirits podcast.
Christ has risen.
Indeed is risen.
All right.
Are you in the car there, David?
You calling while you're driving?
Yes or sorry.
I'm on my way up to San Anthony's monitor right now.
So I'm driving.
Okay. Well, I hope, you know, try not to,
to die or anything live on the radio,
you know, while you're driving.
Keep your hands where they need to be, buddy.
10 to 10 to I promise all right all right all right all right so well how's it going what
road are you on you see you're driving all the way you've seen in these that's that's a long
waste from Tennessee it is just a little bit it's about I don't know 21 hours total but I'm only
driving to El Paso tonight so I'll need about two more hours maybe all right all right so what's on
your mind David from Tennessee on the way to Arizona well you're in you're in a you're in a boring
part of the country too.
So it was probably a good idea to call it.
I think it's real pretty.
Oh, wow.
Let's look at Arizona.
That air in land is very beautiful.
My question was basically this.
I think it was in second Macabees.
After I believe the Macabee had revolted,
the Macabees themselves offered up prayers for their death
to God.
But that was before that...
So how does that fit in with the orthodox view of salvation and the
Herring of Aedes?
Oh, well, I mean, there's a bunch of things that we could say, but I
mean, there is already, and for a long time, there's a hope in the Hebrew
Scriptures of the possibility of being rescued from shield.
Like that is a thing in the Psalms, particularly in the Psalms of
of the sons of Korah.
right. So it's not like that everyone believes, well, when you're dead, you're dead. You know,
and I mean, correct me if I'm wrong here, Father, but isn't it also the case? There's
a sense of, well, they do exist there. And you know, may God have mercy on them so that
things are maybe not so bad.
Yeah. Well, so the incident he's referring to is after one of the battles.
Yeah. What they're like.
Judas and KBS is men, they get sort of
rifle through the bodies.
Yeah, don't they find like these
tally's men's on some of them?
Yeah, pagan Amulets, for pagan Amulets.
Which couldn't really didn't work because they're dead bodies.
But so this is, you know, a divination practice.
This is forbidden, right?
By the Torah.
But so this is happening in the 160's BC, right?
The book of the watchers, for example, in the book of Enic, that section of the book of Enic was written about a hundred years before that.
And in it describes the dead in Hades and says that when the day comes that God intervenes in the world,
Right there are different groups.
Right there's the four caves.
Right there's the righteous who are going to...
to be taken into paradise. There's the the martyrs who are going to receive special rewards
starting with Abel. There are the wicked who are going to get tossed into the like a
fire. And there are the sort of ignorant, right? That's your sort of limbo group who are
just going to stay in Hades and Chiehl forever.
And so there was already this kind of...
idea. And so the Christian view of the hailing of Hades really grows out of those traditions.
The idea that Christ, where he descended into Hades, accomplished that. He sort of did the sort.
Led the righteous into paradise. And presumably pronounced doom, as St. Peter says in first
speeder on the wicked ones, right? And brought the reward.
for the martyrs. Right? So it's it's Christ accomplishing that. So they already had,
but they already had views like that in mind most likely. And so when they go and offer sacrifices,
sin offerings on behalf of those dead soldiers, what they're basically praying and asking God to do
is to reckon those people among the righteous, when that time comes. Yeah.
Does that make sense?
David? Yes sir, yes sir does. Yeah I mean you know the Christian teaching about the
harrowing of Hades and the resurrection and so forth like don't come out of nowhere you know and
this is part of why a lot of the Jewish people are able to accept it whereas a lot of pagans are
like wait what but there is already a basis for it in Judaism you know so all right well thanks very
very much for calling David and drive safely and I hope he-
get to El Paso before it's too late at night.
Thank you, Father.
You're all having a good night.
You too.
All right.
We've got another call from the Holy Land, the land of my,
my blessed beginnings, Virginia.
So Katie is calling from, from Virginia.
Hello, Katie.
How are things in the old dominion?
It's beautiful here.
We're having lovely evening, lots of cool nights and lovely breeze
before the heat kicks up.
Virginia are you if I may ask? I'm in Rone Oak for
Virginia. Rone Oak. Oh, I love Rone Oak. Have there been
no strain? No, that's not that Rone Oak father. Oh,
no Virginia, not North Carolina.
That's what I do with the Crow at hand. That whole region,
Rone Oak, Shenandoah Valley, Lynchburg. I mean, oh, man, that whole
region is great. Great. God bless, you Katie.
Beautiful.
So what's up? Okay, so I'm first of all, I am a new newly baptized orthodox. I've been
orthodox about eight months. Hey, 53 years old. Thank you. I'm 53 years old and I was
a Protestant since I was 11. So I've been listening to the last two podcasts where you've
been talking about dispensationalism.
And I was steeped in it up to my eyeballs just more than you can imagine.
Anyway, I prayed this morning about whether I should call an internet.
And then tonight you guys were talking about Father Steven,
you had said that you had sent a lot of people a therapy over the years.
And I just.
I mean, it's true.
Not really a prank.
People said admission.
I decided to call because my therapist was the one who brought me into orthodoxy.
Hey!
Yeah, so there you go.
You have a couple Orthodox therapists out there.
No, there are.
I've known several.
I've known several and thank God that they're out there.
Okay, so here's my here are my thoughts and they're not they're not corrections per se and
if you'll forgive me in advance.
I just I just had to talk with you guys a little bit about the rebuilding of the temple
in Jerusalem when it would be built the third time within dispensational paradigm, not
with
in the Orthodox. My dad when he became a Christian and I'm going to
verify use Protestant terms. I don't know how to say things any
differently yet. Does that make sense? Okay. Okay. So yeah.
I'm yeah. So anyway, my dad was really interested in N Times and
such and he got this book back in 1988 called 88 Reasons Why The
the Raptor will occur in 1988.
Yes.
And I didn't realize I'm,
yeah, you know,
classic. Yeah anyway so one of the things that they talked about was the
reason the Jews would start the sacrifices again was not because they were
and it wasn't for Christianity it was a sign of Jesus's returning so and
they're actively according to my father and this was a long time ago that
they're actually actively looking for a red heifer from numbers 19 in order to
sacrifice it so they can be
the author. I do all I've heard about that. Oh yes. Yes. I mean this, this, this is the
bread and butter of dispensationism as they always say that this is happening. And now of
course you can like see images being flashed across social media like their red heifer
discovered and here's a picture of it. You know, like it's, it's happening. I feel like
just, you know, since the ad bit of advent of Facebook back in what was it 2006 or seven
that I've seen at least 20, 30.
red heifer pictures, you know, saying that, you know, the purification is about to happen.
The sacrifice is going to begin again, you know, the, the, you know, like it's always just
around the corner. Like there's always some group there that it's about to do that.
And meanwhile, the chief for Bennett in Israel, if you went and asked them, hey, you guys work
on that red heifer stuff, they'd be like, what? You know, it's really, I'm sure there are,
I'm sure that there are some groups that are in Israel because a lot of people
particularly, they move there, they set up the shop, they do all kinds of wacky stuff,
frankly.
Yeah.
So I'm sure there's people there doing, doing weird things.
Absolutely.
There's also, there's been a little bit of development on the whole sacrifice thing.
Like I think we may have mentioned, the first edition of the Scofield reference Bible
talked about them sacrificing animals to Jesus.
Yes.
Like in person.
Well.
sample. And that's.
not in later editions. They've moderated that a little bit.
They have moderated how that all works. There's been some changes in things there in different
dispensational systems. Well, one of the things I wanted, the real thing I wanted to ask you about
was the thing that I really, really struggle with and that's penal substitute, penal substitutionary
atonement because when I read the New Testament, especially Paul, and I get into Romans or Galatians,
It's like
I can hear is the P. N. L. Subtuchinary at home at language.
And that's all I can hear.
And so I just wondered if you guys had any comments on how to get past that.
Yeah.
I've got a book for you.
Actually, I had heard that you had, I had heard that you were going to maybe write a book on the atonement.
I do have a, I do have a, I do have a, a tow room. He do have a, he does.
But it's just the first time you've
logged your own book on.
I hesitate to do so.
But my book on St. Paul does have a
new translation.
Yes. Of his epistle.
I have the book.
I have the book and I was reading
it and it still smacked me
upside the face.
And I think I know it's me.
It's not the translation.
Well, yeah, you're taught to read
it in a certain way.
Yeah.
And that's a hard thing to break
because I know in a lot of even
You like your
not just taught PSA, your taught the PSA is the gospel. Right?
Like that's like the core of Christianity, right? And so
someone coming and saying like, no, right? Yeah.
That's a big paradigm shift.
One thing I think that helps Katie.
One thing I think that could help is like one of the core
ideas of a penal substitute, serotonement is really, I mean,
if you really get down to the real pure version of it, the
the idea is that Jesus is damn.
for you, right? That he is damned. It's not just that it hurts so bad. It's that he's
damned because he's taking the thing that you deserve, which is damnation, right? And
so you can quite literally say that Jesus, Jesus goes to hell, right? Well, yes, and
they put that.
But it's not really harrowing like you guys talk about.
right? Orthodox Christians absolutely believe that Jesus goes to hell, but he's there.
you know, to kick ass and to free among the dead. Yeah. Right. He's free among the dead. He's not
bound. Yeah. Yeah. So the to me, to a crazy talk to a Protestant. Yeah. Sure. Sure. To me, the
thing, the way I approach it with people, right. Because I mean, my parents would receive people
who grew up with that evangelical, the primary touch for you there. I go at it with the old test.
because you could be taught to read St. Paul that way, but you literally can't read the Old Testament that way it's absurd.
So to give you an example, right, I do my parish Bible study that gets recorded and sent out eventually is the whole Council of God podcast, right.
So I know it's somewhere an Exodus and what they're posting, but last night in real time, we're in the book of numbers.
We're way ahead.
And we read this scene where the Levites are being consecrated for their liturgical service at the tabernacle.
Right. And what the text says repeatedly because numbers is very repetitive when you read it.
It says the same thing like five times just to make sure you understand what it's saying.
Says that the Levites are all gathered together and then all the other people from the other tribes are gathered.
The people from the other...
they're going to have to lay their hands on the Levites and offer them as a peace offering to God on behalf of all the people and their sins.
Now, if you want to read that through the Lids of PSA, you would imagine what? They took the Levites and beat them to death.
They laid hands on the Levites to transfer their SIDS onto them and then they took them and punished them for those SIDS and they're forgiven, right?
And that is at work in the text, right?
What the text is clearly saying is the peace offering is we are giving these people out
of all the people, these people we are giving to God to spend their lives serving God as
living sacrifices like St. Paul talks about, right?
And people, some situations just doesn't work there.
And so I've started by telling people, go through the Old Testament, find me one place
where sins are put on an animal and then it's sacrificed.
There aren't any.
Yeah, that's just never a thing.
There aren't.
And I said, so we one place where it says they punish an animal.
Is it what the animal suffers?
Yeah.
There aren't any.
So it really doesn't work in the Old Testament.
You can be taught to read St. Paul's sideways, especially the way it's
translated in English usually to get that, but you can't get it out of the Old Testament.
And then if you read St. Paul, and that's a lot of what I'm doing in my book, if you just
read him in light of the Old Testament, and not just the Old Testament in general, but
the passages in the Old Testament that he quotes, you go back and actually read the Old
passage.
Right.
We're going to do a little bit that in the third.
Well, yeah, the third half actually, right.
Then then that interpretation just doesn't work.
A lot of it comes Katie because people take
passages and turn them into skeleton keys.
You know, like read this, you see what it says that's so clear, but then they don't have
to deal with all of the other stuff in the scriptures that are often being referenced
by whatever the passage that they just brought up actually is.
Like another classic example is Jacob of I loved Esauvah hated.
That's referencing, is that Malachi?
I'm trying to remember Father.
So that's referencing, oh yeah.
That's Obadiah.
Okay, so it's a call back to a specific place
in the Old Testament that happens
long after Jacob and Esau, the men are dead.
It's about their descendants.
So the idea that God loves Jacob and he hates Esau
is not supportable in the actual Jacob, Esau story.
But when the itemites rebel against the Israelites,
Jacob, have I loved Esau, have I hated Israel?
In other words, Israel.
loved, eat them, I've hated, that makes way more sense when you realize it's about those groups of
people, it's about a specific action that that the eedamites took. You know, so that's that's just
another example of like when these things are taken out of context and the sad thing is is that
stuff gets taken out of context and then gets repeated for over and over and over again for centuries
and people just receive and accept that that's how you're supposed to read that passage and they forget
that it's actually that the Bible itself is very to use a modern term hypertextual.
very
everything links to everything else. And if you cut all the links, then you're going to
interpret it the wrong way. You know, does it make sense?
Yes. And I think I think I am going to go back through the Old Testament. That's going
to be quite a project. But my mother-in-law has found out that I've become orthodox. And
she's an old missionary too. Oh, I am. I am. She's just waiting. And I don't want to, but
But here's the thing, I don't want to come out or with.
like combative, like, because that's not what worth an oxy is.
No, you don't have to do that.
It has this beautiful, beautiful humility that, like if she's,
if she's writing to hear you, if she's really writing to hear you,
then then you can talk to her.
But if she's not, then what's the point in, in going into that?
You know, I, you know, if someone can't hear you, then it may even,
even be harmful to your relationship.
That's what I feel like.
You know?
Yeah, that's what I feel like.
Yeah, yeah.
And is it wrong to kind of not tell your old Protestant
buddies that you've converted?
I mean, I don't know your old Protestant buddies.
My old Protestant buddies, if they haven't figured it out
by now.
Well, you've been at it a while.
I forgot eight months under my belt, that's it.
Yes, yes, you're new.
It's okay.
I appreciate y'all taking
my call. I know it was a little off topic, but I really wanted to say that.
This is all asked is it a red heifer? Yeah, no, this is part of our general
arc of dealing with, you know, how do we, how do we really understand Israel?
So yeah, it's within, it's within our general topics. So you're
called welcome. Well, I appreciate you guys a lot. And my husband and I
listened to you guys on the way to work in the morning. So
thank you. God bless you all. All right, we're going to take one more call
and then move on, we're going to take Joshua, who is calling from...
Florida and he wants to bring us all the way back to the first episode of this arc and
Talk about the promises to Abraham is that right Joshua welcome
Florida I'm on the other side. Oh, you're on the other side. I don't know
I mean this is what Mike this is what Mike the flash in the pan to Gan wrote he said that you were from Florida
You're not from Florida. Yeah now California did that not in fact Florida man
West Coast Florida
What part of what
of California. Are you in? Like the in the Empire actually. Oh, while stomping
around. He's from your place there father. Are you in Ukaipa? You betcha? No, I'm in like
Married Attamacula. If you know what Winchester is. Further south. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
I have a question. My question is yeah, the covenant of Abraham.
and how we fall into that as Christians
and coming off of watching West Huff
and hearing all the discussions
on what he was talking about
of can people that are not be Christians be saved
and that and then same thing
when I was watching Jordan Peterson seminar,
every the same question was kind of coming up
with all the non-Christians
and Jonathan Padden.
I had to kind of say like, yeah, you can experience salvation, but the church is really important.
So my question is, what is the difference?
I guess I can understand that outside of Christianity, people can experience salvation as it is
of being freed from our sins.
I guess the question is what's the difference between salvation as a Christian?
in salvation not as a Christian.
That even is a thing.
Yeah, I mean, there's only one salvation, right?
I mean, to be saved is to become, I mean, as as Christ said,
in one of my favorite verses, sons of the resurrection,
the sons of God equal to the angels, right?
That's what salvation is.
That's the destination of salvation.
Um, um,
But it's, I shouldn't say destination really, because it's, it is a continuum, right?
So you can be saved more and more.
You can become more and more, you know, one of the sons of God, more and more like Christ,
right?
And so the Christianity, what that gives us is the straight, clear path of exactly how
to do that, right?
That is the full.
puzzle with all the pieces, right? That is what orthodox Christianity is. Does that mean
that someone who has, who does not have all the pieces that like, oh, sorry, you didn't, you
didn't get that last corner piece in. So go directly to hell, do not pass purgatory, do
not collect $200. You know, no, it does not mean that because, and part of the way we know
this, I think, I mean, I think I hope eventually we will do maybe a dedicated episode on this
question of people outside of.
outside of Israel and one way or another, because it's connected actually some of what we're talking about tonight.
But like the example I like to give is the book of Jonah where the prophet he sent by God to Nineveh.
So this is the Assyrians.
Of course, if you've been listening this up this series, you know that the Assyrians are the worst people on earth at that point.
point. Pre-Merry Noddy Men. Yes. Very, very.
I mean, just horrifying, horrifying people.
And so it's understandable that Jonah, when God sends Jonah to them, he's like, no, I'm
not, I don't want to go there.
You might have mercy on them.
I don't want to go there and be your instrument of mercy on those, on the Assyrians, like those
guys are the worst.
You know, and of course, we know how it turns out.
He sent God, he makes him go basically.
He finally does go and he preaches that Nineveh is going to be overthrown.
and then they repent and God spares them.
And then Jesus himself in the gospels
holds up the men of Nineveh
as a witness against the people of against the Judeans.
Right?
And that they will rise up and stand in judgment
of the generation that's with him there.
So what does that mean?
I mean, the knitted whites.
these serians. These are demon worshiping pagans. And there's no end to, it's not the book of Jonah
does not end with and they all stopped worshiping their gods and began to worship Yahweh, the God of
Israel. Doesn't say that. It just says, and also much cattle. You know, that's how it ends.
And yet their repentance is real and the mercy that God shows them is real and they somehow have this
eschatological place at the end because of their repentance.
repentance. So repentance is real. You can't say, well, it's faith because you're not, you
didn't do all these other things first. Now, if someone is not using all the tools, obviously
that limits them. You know, it doesn't limit God. It limits us. But there's only one salvation.
There's only one salvation, right? There's only one becoming like Christ.
one Christ. There's not a Christ for non-Christians and a Christ for Christians. There's this one Christ.
Right. So the promises are the same and those who do the deeds of Abraham are the offspring of Abraham.
And if you want to do the deeds of Abraham, the clearest way to do that is to become an Orthodox
Christian to live that life faithfully. That is the clearest way. Outside of that, we can't say,
oh, well, you can kind of do that and it'll be fine. We can't say that. God did not say, well,
there's a lesser aversion, but we do know that God is going to
have mercy on whom he's going to have mercy.
And we do know that real repentance is real repentance, even from demon worshipping pagans,
which I mean, that's a pretty extreme example.
I think again, the Assyrians are the worst people on earth.
And God would have had, I mean, he's God.
He can do whatever he wants, but it would have been very understandable if God had not sent
them Jonah.
And it's simply said, you know what?
You guys are the worst.
Fire and brimstone for y'all.
You get the Sodom and Gomorrah treatment.
He could have easily done that.
And everyone would have just said, yep, that's how this goes.
That's not what he did
He sent them Jonah and they repented. They didn't go what we might think of as all the way,
but he did receive, he did accept what they did do. I think that's pretty significant, you know.
You know anything, say, Father, how many of that? Well,
I think a lot of these discussions we have to just like pause
and think about what we're saying.
Right? So if you frame the question is, can someone who's not a Christian be saved?
Be saved is passive. Right? Yeah. So God is the one who is doing the saving. So if we
rephrase the same, this is the same question. This is the same question. This is not a different
question to ask the same question in slightly different language.
Is there any
one who God can't save. Obviously no, right? Yeah. Everyone would
agree no. Everyone who believes that anything resembling the
Christian God would say, no, there's no one who God can't save.
Right. So that means de facto, there's no one who can't to be
saved. Okay. Now there's implied here that like if you say
that well then that means I guess you don't have
do anything, right? The only possibilities are the two extremes. If God could save anyone,
right? If there's nothing that could stop him, nothing humans could do to stop him from
saving someone, then that means humans don't have to do anything at all. They're completely passive
in salvation. That's not a correct corollary. Again, this is the so many people in our society need
to take a logic 101 course.
Um,
alright, like...
If someone comes to you and says,
I'm looking for salvation.
I want to know God or I want to know God better.
I want to come to Christ.
We're going to tell them,
oh, well, you need to come to the church.
You need to become a catacombs.
You need to get baptized.
You need to receive the sacraments.
You need to change these things in your life.
You need to repent of your sins.
You need to do all these things to find salvation.
It doesn't mean someone who doesn't do them can't be saved by God.
It's almost impossible.
But it does mean if that's what you're looking to happen, those are the things you do.
Right.
It is entirely possible that you can live your life the way I do and make it to the age
of 50 without having a heart attack.
Okay.
But if your goal, if you're coming to me as an 18 year old and your goal is to make it
to the age of 50 without having a heart attack, I'm not going to tell you to eat like
me for.
I live the way I do, right?
Because that's not aimed at what you're going to do, right?
Like this is logic stuff, right?
So, and then you get into the, people get into the weeds on this stuff, right?
Like, oh, we'll see. Look, this verse says, you know, what must I do to be saved?
Believe it be baptized. So see, you have to be baptized to be saved.
Oh, but what about the thief on the cross?
Right? Like again, time out. Stop.
Okay.
look what right yes normally God says that you should go and be baptized. If you find yourself
nailed to a cross next to the Son of God the rules can be bent a little right like this might be a
special case. Like it's just ridiculous these arguments we get into these circular arguments they're
They're just ridiculous. They're just semantics.
They're a game that we play.
based on these sort of the theological rules of tit for tat and they accomplish nothing like
This is this kind of stuff is just really simple. I'm not I'm not braiding you caller. I'm I'm an old man yelling at clouds
It's just it's just not
Like we can all agree on some very simple things all right like we all agree. I don't you care if you're not orthodox
Right
I don't care if you're the wildest wild-eyed charismatic evangelical out there, right?
I bet you we agree that number one,
there's nobody who God can't save.
Number two, I bet we agree that if someone comes to us
and says, hey, I want to get saved,
we're gonna tell them to go to church.
If someone says, hey, should I get baptized,
we're gonna say yes.
If someone says, hey, should I be repenting
of my sins to change the way I live?
We're gonna say yes.
Regardless of what you think about faith and works
and blah, blah, blah, blah.
You're gonna tell them to stop sitting
at the repent of the sins they've committed.
Okay, we all are.
are we're all going to tell them to try to obey cops, commandments that doesn't
mean your preaching works or righteousness like let's drop a lot of
the silliness people. Right. It's it's not it has no
course real life, man. I'm a guy who stood around comic book stores arguing
about how Cyclops opens his visors by wriggling his ears and I think these
arguments are stupid.
So anyway, and the red, I don't think this stuff is as difficult as we make it, TLBR.
Yeah, I hope that helps a little bit, Joshua.
What do you think?
Yeah, so I guess what I'm wondering to follow up is, so in the Eskitan, is there to find
kingdom of Israel or like the New Jerusalem is out of the
find kingdom in the age to come. And there'll be citizens and non-citizens.
I would say, I mean, number one, I would say just keep listening to this episode.
Yeah, you're going to, you're trying to jump ahead to the end of the third half.
Yeah, yeah. Yeah. We'll get there. Yeah, we'll get there. We'll get there. So.
Okay. All right. Thank you for calling Joshua from California, not Florida, Mike. He didn't say
floor.
Anyway, yeah, in land empire. All right. Thanks very much. Okay.
Where are we? Alexander the not so great. I don't know just I just make a bunch of people man.
Why is it this half we're gonna all of our Greek listeners are gonna get grumpy? Yeah, I I will say this because we are gonna start talking about Alexander the great I
I mean I you know
Greek friends
Let's sit down a second. I love you. I love you. I love your language. I love your food. I love your churches. I mean
I love just about everything about you
What I do not understand is this whole
Identification with Alexander the man
Was number one a demon worshipping pagan. Yeah, well yeah, pagan is a bit general the pagan Greek traditions of
Right, right, right, but I mean he literally went around becoming a
God King in all the places that he went and conquered.
Like he went through the ritual to become Pharaoh.
He went through the act and I talk about that ritual.
Or still know.
I don't know.
Can't remember how our rated that is.
It's kind of our rated.
Okay, bleep.
Okay, Father Steven just told it all.
Sorry, guys.
And people, people, people, people, people, people,
people can read.
is he the one who wrote the book?
Yes, about Alexander the Great
is a pagan religious figure.
Yes, yes, yes.
Yeah, yeah, go check that out everybody.
Yeah, I'm just saying, I'm just saying.
Okay, okay, Alexander the Great.
Was he that great though?
Well, he was if you were a Macedonian.
Yeah, there you go.
Okay, you just said Macedonian.
Now we're gonna get calls.
What do you mean?
Yes, yes.
So without entering into the whole debate
about what Macedonia is.
Guy, no.
Well, the thing is like it's father was Philip of Macedon.
I mean, he's Macedonia.
I mean, ancient Macedonia covered land
that belongs to multiple different countries now,
like four or five actually.
Yeah.
But so if you're, if you're one of his countrymen, you know,
yeah, he's great.
So the rest of the Greeks did not like it.
so much when he was alive. In fact, Aristotle who had been a teacher had to kind of go on the lamb
from the the Athenians because the Athenians were not super happy with him
because you know he conquered everybody else including the rest of the Greeks.
But so Alexander the great even though he set himself up as Father Andrew said is this sort
sort of divine king and divine emperor.
was never really an emperor in that he never really got to rule over his conquests.
So he, you know, famously conquers the no-world swings over and gets Egypt, then head straight
east goes all the way into India.
It's kind of stalemated eventually in India and as he's returning back from that dies in
his early thirties.
yeah he's like thirty two and and and
apparently people think that he dialed died of West Nile virus and cephalitis. So how
about that?
Averse have to be written. That's right. Don't get that kids. Not comfortable. Yeah, do
not get West Nile. Where is it? Don't get any kind of it. Sephalitis. Just as a good general
I think it's a little more.
I tell my kids that every morning.
But so it's not like we've been talking about e-c-
the Persian Empire, right? But it's not like the Persian Empire. He like he establishes no infrastructure
really. He founds a bunch of cities and names them after himself and one after his horse.
Who's that? But so he does that, right? But by founding cities, this is like as he's traveling and
then he moves on. It's not like he goes and settles there himself. It spends any time, right?
So
He's really a general.
He is a general and a conqueror.
Yeah.
He never really takes a throne as emperor.
Right.
And so as he's dying famously, he's asked, these generals are gathered around him and
ask who's who the successor is, right?
Who's going to succeed him?
Because potentially that person would then establish a throne and become sort of the ruler
of the world.
famously.
Alexander responds, chronotosis, right, meaning the strongest, right?
And just as that implies, the the Diatoki, his successors, his generals all proceed to go to
war with each other, right? To try to decide who is going to be the strongest and who is going to
to rule the world. A bunch of them get killed, a bunch of them get routed. They're end up
three main dynasties established. One over roughly Greece and Asia Minor, one over Egypt and
North Africa, the Tullamies. And then most important for us in terms of the history of Israel and
and Judah and Judea, his general cell Eucos establishes the cell Eucan Empire which
the empire of the east. It's all the eastern holdings. Now over the course of the cell you could
empire, the eastern border is going to continue to move west. Right? So it is going to be sort of
perpetually shrinking in terms of how far east it goes. Because the Indians, the parthians,
eventually, resurgent Persians are all going to start pushing back. Right? At that side of the empire,
there.
And in terms of actually trying to expand, he is the the cell you kids are primarily going
to try to expand by taking tolemie territory.
So the eastern border where the Levant meets the Sinai peninsula, the that southwestern
border of the cell you could empire moves back and forth all the time throughout this period.
the tallies and the so you can make war on each other and push back and
forth. So the capital, the cell you could Emperor Empire is established, Antioch on the
Orante's River. That's Antioch in Syria. That's the Antioch of the Patriarchate of Antioch.
That's the Antioch of the New Testament. Do you know by the way, do you know what they call
that river in Arabic? It has a different name. I do know about this. It's something like
I'm sure I'm gonna mispronounce it, but it's something like...
I see or something like this. And what it means is it means disobedient.
Did you know about this? No, I do not know about it. It's the disobedient river in Arabic. And the
reason they call it that is because all the other rivers in the area flow the other way.
And this one just got to be different. Yeah. So that's the idea they call it the disobedient river
the around yeah which and Antioch is there was
There's not much of an ancient Antioch left.
Was at a strategic point in terms of trade routes
in terms of the capital.
And so when it's established,
we immediately from the get-go get another significant Jewish community.
And that's because at the time of its establishment,
One third of the population of Antioch, the new cat.
is Jewish. Yeah, so that's significant. So Alexandria, Antioch, right, Judea surrounding
Jerusalem, the sounding familiar to anybody. These are these major Jewish centers, which
is why they become major Christian centers, right?
Yeah.
Later on in in early history.
history, uh, Antioch on the
Arantes is going to be the
capital of. So diocese, we
now think of as a church
government term. Right. Yeah,
it was a Roman. But it was a
Roman government term. So there
was there. And these were big
divisions. So there was the
diocese of Africa, the
diocese of Europe, Europa, the
diocese of the east.
An anti-Oc was the capital of the
all the way through the Roman period.
Yeah, interestingly, in still in Greek, if I remember this correctly, like diocese roughly means
like what we would consider as patriarchy and perish whatever the exact Greek form means basically
what we would consider a diocese. It's the area that's ruled over by a single bishop and diocese
is that space that I was ruled over by a synod of pushups.
So, yeah, so that's a big, so Antioch, not just during the
Silicon Empire, is this major city. It's named after Antioch
as the first who, like Alexander, named a bunch of cities
after himself. So there are several Antiochs. You see a few
of them, like in the book of Acts, there's Antioch in
Pasidia to distinguish it from Antioch in Syria or Antioch
on the Aron Tees.
So there's multiple antioxious, like there's multiple Alexandria's, but there's one big important famous one.
Right. And then all the others.
So the other thing that happens with the cell you could, kings is they very much
follow the model that Alexander tried to adopt of presaying themselves as divine kings.
So they adopt all of these titles, right? Antiochus III, so tear, right?
savior. And now the most infamous one. And again, the most relevant one for our trip through
the history of Israel, Judah, and Judea, and Tychus IV who took as his reigning title,
Epiphanies, meaning that he's the manifestation of a God on earth.
Oh, it doesn't just mean he has really good ideas on a regular basis.
No, I can't even...
Eureka!
Oh no, that's right.
So weak.
We can't a piffin. No, it has a go. Yeah. Yeah. So and Tych is the fourth epiphanies
Like many
Salihukin botterics goes to war with the Talaamies. Right. This is as one they do. Yeah, it's trying to take some more territory
on the south the western frontier and
It goes very badly
Not only does he not get any territory. He loses territory
Yeah, he is very upset with us, right?
And of course, being a God king, this can't possibly have anything to do with bad planning on his part.
Or right, bad combat strategy or, you know, superior numbers on the other side or supply.
Nothing so rudimentary is that clearly something happened to sway the gods from his side.
Yes, traders and our midst, quizzlings as it were.
So someone has done something.
He and his advisors light upon the idea that, hey, you know what, we got these people.
There's a concentration of a Judea.
There's other group that's kind of like them in Samaria.
And then there's people like them spread out all over the place.
They won't worship the gods.
They won't participate in the sacrifices to the Greek gods.
Right.
And the gods see that they're ticked about it.
And that's why you lost.
And so...
I mean, that begins a long tradition, right?
Yes.
Of paganism.
And so, and...
I think this is in Christians.
Yeah, this is going to become very common, right?
And so, he decides to engage in some
penal substitutionary atonement and take out his wrath on the Jews.
Um...
So there's no forgiveness here. It's just wrath. So he goes into Judea and
interjuresome proper sacs it, sacs the temple, right? Takes everything valuable,
ceases it, goes into the temple, sacrifices pigs on the altar to Zeus, which
referred to in scripture.
the abomination that leads to desolation, which is bad. And not only does that, then that kicks off,
right? His ruining of the temple, right? Making it unusable until it's cleansed and restored
again and rebuilt. His doing that touches off then a persecution throughout the cell you could
the Empire of Jews.
And a lot of that ends up getting centered actually at Antioch, as you might expect being
his imperial capital, and having a large Jewish population right there, right at hand.
And it's important that this is not an attack on an ethnicity, which as we've said, that
concept didn't exist then.
This is not a racist thing.
This is not, or notice that, and you can see that by the attack.
He doesn't just go with...
start killing them willy-milly, right? Like kill all of them. Yeah. Right? Because he doesn't have
those racial genetic, those kind of archetypes yet. Right? He's going to take the modern age and
modern pseudoscience to get us to the point where we can have that kind of genocide.
He's, right, his attack is on Uday's most. His attack is on their way of life. He wants to break them
of keeping Torah.
and have them worship the Greek gods like everybody else. That's his goal. Yeah. Now if he can't get them to do that
He's fine with killing them. Right. Right. But those are your options. Right and so it's not just worship the Greek gods
It's literally eat pork
Now given that pork it was probably from a pig sacrifice to an idol, right?
20th of the Greek Gods.
It's literally break the Torah.
And the most important dramatization of this
is the Maccabeean martyrs in Second Maccabees.
The Maccabeean martyrs had a major Jewish shrine
for centuries after this in Antioch
that became a Christian shrine later on.
The Maccabeean martyrs are an old man named Eliezer
and a woman in her seven sons.
You can read this.
detail in second Macabees. But essentially the TLDR is the Greek authorities tortured, brutally
tortured her seven sons to death in front of her. Yeah. To try to get them and her and Aliezer to
eat pork. Eat pork. By the way, we have someone in the chat on YouTube who is really wanting us to
talk about the whole drunken elephant thing.
all of this invitation to read first back of these. Yeah.
Three first and then accused J. R.
of talking of blatant, uh, plagiarism. Um,
yeah.
So, so these two months drunk, I don't think so. No.
Yeah. Sorry Nate. We're sorry Nate. We're not, we're not doing
the drunken elephant thing. But you're right. It's a different
podcast. It's this period. Yeah. That's a different
So yeah, so she sees her, says we tortured death refuses, right?
But important here, right?
Important here is what we see in Second Maccabees.
This is a Jewish text, not a Christian text yet, right?
Christianity adopts it.
I know some of you out there are Christians that don't have any
in your Bibles, but trust me.
I should directly get the director's cut of the Bible guys.
Yeah.
So, right, is that while this is happening, when you look at the prayers that are being
prayed by the sons, by the mother, right, during these martyrdoms, what you see is what's
really being set forward here is the whole theology related to martyrdom.
Yeah.
That is sort of already established by the time you get to the New Testament.
Right?
So when St. Stephen gets stoned, it's interpreted through.
this kind of lens, right? When St. James gets killed, it's interpreted through this kind of lens.
When Herod kills St. John the Four-Hunter, it's interpreted through this kind of lens because the
idea of martyrdom already exists. Yeah, and I mean, just think back in the rest of the Old Testament,
guys, this really isn't a thing up to now. It's not. Yeah. The preceding parts of the Hebrew Bible
are more about trying to get somebody in
Israel to actually keep the Torah, not trying to force them to break it. Right. Right. Yes.
So in some ways we have a remnant. We have a faithful remnant here. Yeah. They're trying to break.
Right. Yeah. And they don't break. Right. But the prayers that they're praying during this talk
about them offering themselves to God as a sacrifice of a tonement on behalf of the sins of the people.
They're being murdered, but they're offering their death nonetheless as a sacrifice, as a pleasing
sacrifice to God.
Right?
And what about their death?
Not so much the pain and suffering as their obedience even to the point of death.
They're making that an offering to God on behalf of the people.
Right?
understanding this is critical to understanding how the early
Jewish Christians immediately understand the death of Christ.
Because they already have this paradigm that a person, a righteous man who is put into
this kind of situation, who is murdered for being righteous, is sort of offering himself
as a sacrifice on behalf of the people.
So if the Messiah does that, if the Son of David does that, if the Son of David does that,
So,
God does that. Yeah, they've got a
a pair of murder for his righteousness and offers his his life and his obedience and his death
to God as a pleasing sacrifice. That is sort of the ultimate fulfillment filled full, filled
overflowing of this idea. Right. I'm doing this on behalf of the people.
And so this is this is crucial to understanding this core Christian idea
of
Christ's death as his voluntary self offering as a pleasing sacrifice to God the Father.
And so worth noting here because this most often doesn't get noted that the Greeks went after
the Samaritans too. Yeah, I mean, as far as they're concerned, Samaritans are just as weird.
Yeah.
They probably don't even really know the difference.
Right.
So the Samaritans, as we talked about a little last time, the Samaritans are from our modern
perspective of mixed ethnicity.
They are people from the northern kingdom who remained in the land after the Assyrians,
who have intermarried with the people from other parts of this Syrian empire who were brought there.
and settled there. They were there obviously throughout the 70 years of the exile. So when the
Judahite refugees come back, the Samaritan's were already there. And the Samaritan's had what we
now today call the Samaritan Pentateuch, which is another version of the Torah. We don't have time
time to go down a huge...
rabbit hole about it tonight. That sounds like a future, a future
episode. A lot of new travel super.
Because you have to remember the Samaritan Pentateuch is put
together and stuff way before any copy of the Torah we have in
Hebrew. Right. Now we don't have any copies that old. But
There are places where there may be...
earlier readings of things or where what's their shed's light on something
confusing in the Hebrew, right? So there's lots of interesting things there. But
the problem with assuming too much about that, and this is what makes studying
the Samaritan penitent tricky, is that it was also deliberately altered.
to make the Samaritans like
the actual like they're the real Israel not these two diets. Right. And when I say rewritten
I mean like stuff in Genesis is rewritten things are changed. Little stories are added and
stuff. Two for example a bunch of things happen on Mount Garesum which happened to be in
Samaritan territory instead of say Mount Horib. Right. Stuff in the in the regular Torah
which they then used to justify having built their own ten-
on Mount Gharism, which was a temple that was up and functioning at this time. They were
doing the cycle of feasts, right? So they're having Passover with lambs and stuff. They're
doing these things and claiming to be sort of the real recipients. Of course, the returning
Judahite exiles considered themselves the real faithful remnant, right? And these Samaritans
are not only, you know, do...
UBS has to be Israelites. They kind of seem like foreigners, but they clearly have a corrupted
Torah and they clearly are doing things places where they're not supposed to be doing them.
And worst of all, saying that the Judahites are illegitimate, right? They're not the legitimate
ites. Right followers. So between the two, there is this sort of rivalry. But again, they're
both under foreign domination.
at this point, it's a weird kind of sibling rivalry or weird cousin rivalry, going on,
it's going to get worse going ahead. That's why we're kind of introducing it now. But
from the Greek perspective, the Seljukin perspective in this persecution, the Samarits
are just as bad. They're not worshipping the pagan gods either. So they also face a wave
of persecution from the Greeks.
Um.
Yeah, so it's it's you see this kind of thing they really did not understand what was going
on with the Jews or the Samaritan or any they didn't understand any of this the Greeks didn't
the Romans didn't either. My favorite example of that is near the end of the book of Acts
when the the Roman governor has to you know he's sending St. Paul to Rome for his trial
And he has to kind of send a document like here's why I'm referring this case to you, right?
like here's the crime he's accused of or whatever.
And the note he says is,
it is a dispute between him
and the religious authorities of Judaism,
they claim this person, Jesus is dead
and he claims he's alive.
That's what gets referred to the emperor.
Yeah.
Like, I'm not really at no idea what's going on.
Right?
We got...
But you do say this guy's dead.
We got this other juice saying he's alive.
I don't know.
They want to kill each other or something.
I whatever said, you know,
I bought a comma past.
Yeah.
But really, yeah, the Greeks were the same like they just,
they didn't get this, right?
Like at all, right.
Um,
so this oppression, this brutal oppression, right?
The destruction, the, the, the,
uh, the desecration of the temple,
which sees as it's
services. The persecution of Jewish people, this then spurs or a vault known as the Maccabeean
Revolt. Yeah. Yeah. And first Maccabees is really about the history of this of this revolt.
Revolt begin is started by a Levi priest named Matathias and his sons. We're going to find out
about several of his sons.
As we go forward.
But so, Mathias and his sons begin this revolt.
They're sort of the leaders.
They say we need to, we're not taking this anymore.
We're fighting back against these pesky Greeks.
And so, Mathias himself starts the revolt.
circa 170
He is sort of the leader until he dies in 167 and 167 Judas Mccabius, which means
Judah the Hammer.
It's a cool name.
Yeah, takes over.
He's the leader of the revolt from 167 to 160 BC.
And then...
he is succeeded as leader by his youngest brother.
So, Matatize's youngest son, Jonathan Apthus,
who is leading the revolt from 160 to 143 BC.
Now, I'm ashamed that I never have looked this up,
but I mean, are the Maccabees texts,
are they named after Judas Maccabees or Maccabees?
Yes.
Okay, so yeah, so he lends his nickname, really.
Yeah.
Okay. So, and so within this they manage to take control of the temple area and the temple
is rededicated. This is where Hanukkah comes from. The, because they only have enough oil
for one day right because you're supposed to
keep the, what we now know as a menorah, right, the candlestand, the temple is supposed
to be perpetually lit and perpetually burning. They only had enough oil for it to for one
day, but miraculously it lasted for eight days. I once heard a Jewish comedian say, you
know, that there's now a major holiday because they just found a really good product. Wow.
imagine if you brought us with
Arby knife back in time.
But so that's that's where the
feast of Hanukkah comes from.
It's a modern celebration as far as I
could tell it is lost all
association with the Maccabee
and revolt.
Yeah, I mean, who even knows about
that?
Right. It's just lighting the
menorah, spitting a dreidel.
There is there is Jewish
Christmas.
I was there is a there is a Jewish.
I think they're an Acapelogrupp
called the Maccabees.
So
That's a thing. Well, there you go. Yeah.
So I made several years ago, they may still be out there in
circulation on the internet. I made a bunch of Judas
Maccabee's Hanukkah memes. If any of you, I feel free to
continue to circulate them. I did not know you were a
meme, sir, father, Steven. Oh, yeah. No, I made like,
because I'm like, look, I felt bad. I'm like, somewhere
out there, there's a 14 year old Jewish boy who wants
something like cool and super.
awesome, like a picture of Judas Bikhabias, like Hacke and a Greek guy with a sword for
his Sonic and Card, right? This is just want a picture of a menorah or a
tradele. Come on, man. So, you know, yeah, I tried to help. I tried to help.
So Jonathan Apfus becomes this transitional figure because under him really
the
The revolt is finally successful in the sense of there being a kind of independent Judea
And this is where things start to go a little crazy
because
Not only is Jonathan Apthas ready to make himself king now
But he makes himself high priest. Oh
No, now previous to him being high priest
Under Judas Bacabius, another brother had been made high priest, but at least it was a different person.
Yeah.
Priest King's, that's not a thing amongst his children.
But at the Feast of Booths,
right, the Feast of Tabernacles to go in 153 BC, Jonathan presides, Jonathan Atphus presides
his high priest while also being king.
And he cement.
the successful revolt by making a bunch of treaties with foreign nations. That's also against
the Torah. Yes, which you're also not supposed to do, right? Yeah. So yeah. So and amongst those
foreign powers are the Spartans. And we've talked about the Spartan treaty before on the show
because that's the one that meant that refers to the Spartans as fellow descendants of Abraham.
Yes, right, and we're like what?
We talked about this a little
earlier this, right, the Philistines are included in Deuteronomy 4 and these other things that,
you know, some of the Coffinary and some of those Greeks are somehow descended from Abraham.
And then also one with Rome. And that's the one that backfires in a huge way later on.
But all of this is to help protect them from the Seljukids, the Greeks coming back in and
taking over. Right. So they make treaties with these other powers that
try to deter that. Now we have these allies, defense treaties. Hey, you don't want to mess with the Spartans and the Romans. So stay away, Spiro.
But so we now begin what is called the Hasmonian or Hasmanian dynasty.
And parallel to the emergence of this dynasty of
priest kings because that's what it's going to be. We're going to be kings of Judea. There's
another movement that begins and this is a movement anybody who's read a single page of the New
Testament has heard of that's the Pharisees. Yes, there are these radical reactionaries. Well,
Now I need to prepare you, I need to prepare you all because
I know you've all been taught to read the New Testament in a certain way.
Thanks, Martin Luther.
In a certain way, where the Pharisees are the bad guys.
Okay.
That is incorrect.
The Pharisees are not the bad guys in the New Testament.
Rice never says they're even wrong about anything.
Yeah.
He says they set Moses.
do whatever they tell you, right? Never says it. There are two bad things that Christ says about
the Pharisees. The main one is he says they're hypocrites, right? Yeah. Do what they say but don't
do as they do because they're hypocrites, right? They talk a good game. The things they say, the things
they teach are correct, Jesus is saying, but they don't practice them themselves and that's the problem,
Right.
the hypocrisy because as St. Paul will say, it's not the hearers of the Torah, but the doers that are
justified. Right? So that's the big one. The second one will get into in just a second,
after we talk about what being a Pharisee is all about. Okay? So the reason the Pharisees rise up
over against the hazman hands and particularly rise up in Judea.
is the word Pharisee comes to a word that means to be set apart. Right, to be set apart.
To be set apart from what? Hmm. That's the question. And it, and especially throughout
this period, it primarily means to be set apart from the hazmanans, from their whole system.
And their whole system means both the government, their kingship.
which the Pharisees said was illegitimate,
because they're Levites, not Judahites.
Right?
So their kingship is illegitimate,
and their high priesthood is illegitimate,
because they're also kings, right?
And they're not from the Zadakites.
We'll come back to that.
They're not descended from Zadak,
which with the temple was restored,
that's where the priesthood was supposed to come from,
then is a heal.
So they thought both of those were illegitimate.
They thought the temple, therefore,
was only quasi-legitimate.
The reason they thought it was quasi-legitimate
even is that it was built before the Hezmoneans.
But the fact that the Hezmoneans have controlled it
where the high priest there made it very problematic.
And so the
Pharisees throughout their existence in this period showed a preference for the synagogue system.
This is one of the reasons why when you get to the New Testament, there's a prevalence of synagogues as Father Andrew pointed out even in Judea itself.
Yeah, right. We're the temples there because I mean, there's stuff we need to go to the temple to do in terms of sacrifices because God told us to do it, but
that.
No.
No, like things are like this.
kind of illegitimate guys. I mean, are the Hezmonians, are they even Levites?
They're not even Levites, are they?
No, they are Levites. Oh, they are Levites. Okay. They are.
They are Levites, but they're Levites from the wrong family and Levites aren't supposed
to be king. Yeah. Right. Right. Right. Right. And you're definitely not supposed to be
king and I preach at the same time. Um, okay. So, uh, yes, this is all wrong. Right.
So that's, that's a lot of what they're separating from. And there's sort of ideology is simple.
the radiology.
is we're supposed to be following the Torah. Right? Yeah.
What God has said to this mess, the exile at all is not keeping the Torah. Right. And so God
wants us to do. And what we need to do, if we want him to send the Messiah and intervene in history
and do all these things and remove the curse from us and do all these things, is we need to keep
the Torah. It's pretty straightforward. Yeah. So this idea that the that the hismoneans represent
But they represent, you know, God's salvation or whatever or the Messiah. Yeah, they're like that's that the Messiah wouldn't do that
Yes, you know, yeah, no you are not sir. Yes
Not even close right
Kind of an anti-Mazai
Right, and so now they aren't gonna be like the Essings
right? Who are so disgusted with the whole situation that they opt out?
completely. Yeah, so they're actually going to the desert. Right.
There's actually serving as kind of prophetic role though, almost like they're remain there.
Yeah, they're calling. They're calling the rulers to repentance. Right. Right.
There is part of that. And this gets us to to to Jesus second criticism of the Pharisees,
which is also a criticism that you find later on in rabbinic Judaism of the Pharisee movement.
that part of how they do that, part of how they bear witness.
part of how they set themselves apart is to very publicly set themselves apart.
So as Christ says, they make their factories broad and they're
they're very
they're ostentatious about they pray long prayers in public right part they make a point
right they're sort of publicly protesting all the time
right against the whole right uh disordered
system. Right. And so this sets you up for an obvious temptation to pride. The very act
of publicly presenting yourself as one set apart, who is better than pure than holier than
the regular person sets you up to fall into pride and arrogance. Right. And hypocrisy.
And so that's the other criticism that we see Christ say, but those are the two criticisms
of the Pharisees, right?
That said, right, that try to keep the Torah that is what they're supposed to be doing,
right?
No matter what your view is about the New Testament, at this time in history, keeping
the Torah is what Jewish people are supposed to be doing, right?
Yeah, so they're not wrong about that, right?
And yes, they do get into fine details, right?
Because somebody has to do it. Well, wait, how much is work?
What constitutes work on this Sabbath?
Right? And they have debates about these things, right?
And they get caricatured a lot for that.
But even those little fine details, if you read carefully,
Christ doesn't really criticize. Right?
So for example, when he's pronouncing woe on the Pharisees, which
is serious. That's basically cussing them out. That's basically telling them they're damned.
For their hypocrisy and stuff, right? That passage we read during Holy Week,
where Christ is being really un-Christ-like in the way he talks to people. Really mean...
Right? Christ says, what he thinks he says is, you tithe from your mint and your dill and your
human.
But the greater things of the Torah, justice and righteousness and mercy, these you ignore.
Right? Okay. We kind of just stop there. Right? Oh, yeah, that's a Pharisee for you. He's sitting
there in his herb garden, cutting off a tenth of his herbs, you know, but he doesn't care about
people and he doesn't care about these bigger things. But Christ goes on to say, these things you
you should have done while not neglect.
the others also. Christ doesn't say those little things aren't important. Those little things of
the Torah aren't important, just the big, just the broad strokes. No. He says, you can't miss the
forest for the trees. Both the forest and the trees are important. Yeah. Right. That's what he actually
says. So that's a different kind of criticism of the Pharisees. He's the way we normally read it.
So the Pharisees are this group that are opposed to the
Hasmoneans in their system.
And it's important to introduce them here because we're not going to have, we don't have time, time pills.
I mean, I could go all night, Father Andrew, not so much.
Of the policy.
But I like to sleep more than three hours.
So the, but throughout the, we're now going to go through the Hasmonean dynasty sort of relatively quickly and talk about the Hasmonean.
that has won Ian.
priest kings, high priest kings. And throughout this, we could go into detail on things done by each one. But there are literally kings who are going to mention,
like Judah Aristobulus, who at one point had 6,000 Pharisees murdered, for speaking out against his, for condemning him for the Torah.
So the Pharisees really do have a role at this.
that's more like St John the Four,
or St John the Baptist, V Herod, right?
Like then we give them credit for,
because we typically don't give the Pharisees credit
for anything.
They're again the bad guys,
but they're actually the good guys through this period.
Yeah, they're the ones who are in the right.
And the fact that they're set apart,
the fact that they never buy into this corrupt system,
When that corrupt system gets destroyed by the
Romans, that's why the Pharisees survive and become rabbinic Judaism.
Yeah, because they're not, they're not invested in that system.
Right. They had already, right, separated themselves from it.
So our first real, considered the first of the Hasimony and dynasty is Simon Tassie,
who's another one of the sons of Adythias, right, who becomes King and high priest in 142 BC.
Right.
Yeah.
And he sets out what's going to become the project of the Hasmoneans, which is
how are we going to receive the rest of the promises of Abraham?
How is the curse going to be gone?
How are we going to get the land back?
How are we going to do this?
We're going to do this by force.
Yeah.
We're going to sure that will go very well.
Yes, we're going to take it back.
Okay.
And that conquest really begins with his son, John here, canis.
John here canis is an infamous figure. Right. John here canis. I know a lot of our
Protestant friends have never heard of him, but John here canis is the guy who
becomes the model for like yours. We'll talk more about this a little in a
little bit, but for the zealot groups in the New Testament, for the would-be
the Messiah of the New Testament who are.
overthrew the Romans, John here canis is their role model. Yeah, he's the guy. He's the guy.
Yeah. Like when you think when you see people that it seems that their idea of a Messiah is a guy
with a sword in his hand who kicks all the Romans or Greeks or whoever out, this is what this
is modeled after. Yes. And keep in mind, John here canis while he's doing all the things we're about
to talk about is also the high priest.
Man, he goes in Conquered Samaria and Idouméa.
So the regia is what's left of the people of Edom.
The descendants of Esau.
Edom had also fallen eventually to the Babylonians.
But there's a remnant of people descended from the Edomites living in the land.
But that whole area in the southern transjordan gets conquered by John Hercannis.
That territory
back in Deuteronomy before God said don't take a single foot of it.
But John here can is does. And when I say he conquers these places, so when he goes in conquer
Samaria, he not only kills a lot of Samaritans, he goes and destroys their temple on Mount
Gherism. Levels it to the ground. Okay. And so at this point, that sort of weird cousin rivalry,
rivalry between the Samaritans and
the Judeans takes a very different turn. Yeah, this is now not just those people are weird and
have a weird Bible. It's that there's this destruction of their temple thing, you know, so there's
it's a mutual hatred. It's not just that the Judeans, oh, the Judeans think some
Samaritans are weird. The Samaritans have historical grievance against Judeans as a result of this.
Yes.
He is
a
King and High Priest until 104 BC when his son Judah Aristobulus becomes King.
He's only King for a short time for about a year, but in that year he conquers Galilee,
the area around the Sea of Galilee.
And then he is succeeded by his son Alexander Janayus, becomes King and High Priest in 103 BC.
Who conquers it's rare and what's he conquers in Teraea? This is the biggest that independent Judea gets as an independent kingdom
or a sort of time out around
90 BC it's at its height
in terms of size and it is about as big at that point as Israel ever was in
the in
It's history. It's not the same territory
That way.
like David's kingdom had, but it's about the same amount, right, as Solomon's kingdom
at its height, the same square mileage, right, even though it's different territory, more
territory in the southern transjordan less than the northern transjordan, etc.
Alexander, Alexander Janayas dies and is succeeded by his wife.
What?
Salome?
Salome.
Sandra. Yeah, so this is where we get that name, right? Selama? You say, yeah, you made me
noticing some of these. Notice how common a lot of these names are in the New Testament.
How many methyases and Matthews are there? Yeah. How many signs really Maccabeeans? Maccabeean
era name. Yes. John's Judas is. So this is so yes. So all this all of this history, all of this
stuff is very present for the for the Jews of the New Testament. Yes. Like they're naming
their kids.
People. Yes. Yes.
They're naming their kids after these people because for a big portion of the people this is we're going to talk about this is still their ideology.
Salome by the way is based on the Hebrew name Shlomzian, which is a feminized form of Solomon.
Solomon.
So she was Alexander Gideos's wife.
She becomes queen, 76 BC.
She does not become high priest.
Even the Hezmoneans would not ordain women priests.
So instead when Alexander Gideos dies her son,
John here canis the second becomes the high priest.
the high priest. So 76 BC.
For Sun, John, her canister second becomes high priest.
She becomes queen.
So it is separated again briefly
because she dies in 67.
And when she dies in 67, she says,
I want my son John, her canister second,
the high priest to be the new king and high priest.
So in 67, he also becomes king.
So as of 67, John, her canister second is king and high priest.
Here's the problem.
He is a brother.
Right?
His brother, so he's John here can't it's the second.
His brother is Judas Aristopolis II.
So they're just naming their kids after previous members of the dynasty.
Judas Aristopolis II wants to be king and high priest instead of his brother, his older
brother being king and high priest.
And so Judas Aristopolis II makes a deal with the, or John here can't it's the second.
Sorry.
No, Julia Aristotle says...
second, makes a deal with the Parthians and says, hey, I need to get rid of my brother.
And basically, abducts his brother. It has the Parthians take him as a prisoner. So John
your cat is the second disappears from the picture one year later, one year after becoming
King. His brother, Judah, Erysadboulos II in 66 BC becomes King in high priest.
Okay. Now here's the problem.
Stuff's going on in the background.
If you know some Roman history,
you know that there's stuff going on in the background.
In this period of the 60s,
there's a bit of a Roman civil war going on
between Julius Caesar and Pompey.
Two generals.
Yes, this is the late Republican pre-imperial era.
Right.
The reality is both, both Pompey and Julius Caesar are trying to make themselves the
first Roman emperor for all intensive purposes.
Yeah.
It's not going to work out for either of them.
It's pretty dead.
Spoilers.
But so in the midst of this, all this going on, Pompey, right, is active in the east.
Caesar has been active as a general in the West, right? He completed the conquest of Gaul across the Rubicon all that
Pompey's been active in the east he goes and annexes Judea
Just says hey guess what guys you're part of Rome now
And he does that with a Roman army
So this isn't like you know, hey, we delivered a letter
Good news your annexed a Rome. No, this is he shows up with troops
Thanks for watching.
And famously, Barge is into the temple.
Barge is into the most holy place,
and nothing happens to him.
He finds nothing there.
There's another sign, nothing happened to him
that something's wrong vis-à-vis the temple.
In terms of God's presence there.
But also, this is where he sort of starts
the Roman fascination with Judaism
because he talks about how the Jews worship their God,
so lamentees just with their mind,
because there was no idol in the temple.
nothing there behind the curtain. Um, just
with so he at that point wants to just get rid of the
hasmonians. Right. He's like, these people seem pesky and
untrustworthy. Right. Rome will just rule here. We're all a
pointed governor. Um, but he gets contacted by John here,
can't it's the second who's over that Parthean prison.
I'll do a deal with you.
you guys. I'll be good. I'll be
I am way cooler than my brother. Right.
Right. He's no good. Get rid of him. Put me back in the spot. Right.
Make me king and high priest again. And, uh, and I'll be your loyal subject.
Right. I'm, uh, yes, sir. Right. I love you, Romans. Okay.
So he does a deal. Uh, Pompey gets John, your cat is the second released.
It's 63 BC. John, you're getting to see
becomes king and high priest again. And his brother, Judah, Aristopolis II, who you served him, gets
hauled off to Rome as a prisoner. So the worm has turned. But I think so goes so well for John
here, Candace II going forward. Certain precedents have been established. And so his son, his own son,
Okay, and TIGGETUS MATIFIAS.
in 40 BC decides he's sick of waiting for old dad to die so that he could become king at high
priest and a Tignus Mata Thias goes and again abducks his dad cuts off both of his ears. Yeah like which
okay which seems like a weird thing to do but you can't be high priest if you are rhymed. He's
He's maimed, he's mutilated.
Now he can't ever come back as hype.
Yeah, so he knows what his dad did with his uncle. Right. It's like I get rid of him for good
this time. They've merged King and high priest. So if you maim the King slash high priest,
then he's he's out. Right. So now, Joseph says he actually bit off his ears. Oh, that's, wow,
that's like a certain boxer that we call his own father's ears. Yeah. We're likely they're
just cut off. It's funny. I mean, it's funny to me. It's like, oh, let's, let's follow this
Little priv-
another Torah about yes exactly how the Torah said things should be set up yes
Gali cutting off your father's gear mutilated your father and sending him into exile right so you can become
King of the high priest that's how succession works that's worth it in a cling on ship man
at least there you get to die with honor
So in 40 BC, at Teginus Matatheus becomes the King in High Priest.
and is going to be the last Kagan high priest
from the Hasmonean dynasty.
Yes.
So the years as dad gives them back to the Parthians.
But in the background here again,
if you know some Roman history,
there's another Roman civil war ramping up.
That's between Mark Antony and Octavian.
Octavian's gonna become Caesar Augustus
And Mark Antnis, hang it out with Cleopatra.
And the last of the tolamis in Egypt.
And is getting ready to make some moves.
And he decides, man, these has modients are more trouble than their worth.
Pompey should have gotten rid of them when he has a chance.
And so he has a ticket to some NFI is executed in 36 BC.
This is like five years before the Battle of Actium between him and Octavian.
And
It's not totally clear how he was killed
because different sources say different things.
And this is mentioned, his execution of a Tiga Dysmaticias
is mentioned, for example, in Plutarch's life of Mark Antony.
So we have sources on this.
This isn't just something we know about
from obscure Jewish bits of history.
This is world history stuff.
So, Roman sources, including Plutarch.
say that the Romans beheading him.
Right.
Which would have been appropriate because he's a king after all.
That's that's if you're a Roman, that's the way that you kill someone in a nice, respectful
way.
It's the fastest way that they know how to take someone out.
Right.
Josephus says he was crucified.
Yeah, which is the worst way you kill someone as far as the Romans could.
That's the I stomp on you and spit in your face and you know, make you look terrible
in front of everyone.
Yeah, so it's unclear which of those is actually true. I mean, you could go either way. Yeah. Yeah.
But or knowing the Romans, it could have somehow been both, you know, but
they were cruel people. But so
while that's the end of the Hasimonean kings, there are of course still going to be high praise.
And so...
So his son, Aristobulus III in 36 BC, becomes the new high priest but there are no more
Hasmonian kings.
But he is high priest establishes, now this high priesthood coming from him, and it's
not going to be a direct line because there's going to be assassination and chakainery
and all the same kind of stuff we saw with the kings, with the high priests.
But that is the line that is the group, the priests, the high priests.
decided for Aristotle is the third. These are the Sadducees.
Yeah, and the reason why they call themselves that is it's from Zedok, who is, you know,
the one that the line of priests are supposed to be coming from amongst the Levites.
And so the idea is that there's Zedokites. So Sadducees is basically just
Sadduke. Yeah, exactly. It's a yeah. Yeah. Now they are not decided from Zedok.
Yes, propaganda.
There's yet.
Yeah. To try to legitimate themselves, right? But so that's who the Sadducees are who we see the New Testament. This is why the Pharisees and the Sadducees hate each other.
Right. Yeah. Because the Sadducees are the remnant of this line of the Hasmoneans who not only were wicked and were stood up to by the Pharisees but who regularly massacred Pharisees.
This is why there's this antipathy between them.
But you can also see how the Hasmonean ideology continues in the Sadducees.
The Sadducees don't have anything about it after life.
They're not expecting God to intervene.
They're not expecting a resurrection.
They're all about making this stuff happen themselves in this world.
Over against the Pharisees.
So to replace the Hasmoneans, since there's not going to be any more Hasmonean kings,
uh
the robins do a brief experiment. One they're they're gonna regret this one and get rid of it too.
But they do a brief experiment of that brief experiment is the Herodians.
Yes so there's Herod. Herod the great the first one. He is an Idumian so he is descended from the
Edamites. Yes, so he's a descendant of Esau. So he is, he is an Abrahamite, but not
a Judean and not even Israelite.
Really?
Yeah.
Right.
Now, they don't just put him on the throne that the
Hasmoneans had.
They carve up the Hasmonean territory.
So they separate Galilee, Samaria, Judea, right?
They deliberately cut it all up.
Right.
So they've already got that.
and they make herod not a king.
Romans don't like the title king.
They make him, even though he's referred to as a king by the people there and like to refer to himself as one.
From the Roman perspective, he's named the ethnarch.
Yeah, which is the ruler of the people, right?
And that's very important. He was not the ruler of the land. He was not the ruler of the natural resources.
He was not the ruler of anything the Romans cared about. He was the ruler of those people who are wandering around on our land.
And that's it.
And so he had a duty to help them keep those people in line and not causing problems.
Now, despite this, or maybe because of it, the resulting insecurity of his position,
Herod really wanted to be great.
He's kind of a sad pathetic figure in his-
I know.
Like this guy, he starts slipping into Cleopatra's DMs as it were.
Yes.
He tried to relance Cleopatra and failed.
right which is like clip
patches like okay, look, I've been with Julius Caesar, I've been with Mark Anthony, and
you are.
Yeah.
You know.
And then screech comes walking in like do you eight Zach Morris?
Wow.
You ain't even yeah, no, is this our first save by the bell, right?
Have you made others that I just not even Slater, man?
You're screech.
Get out of here.
Okay.
But he immediately tries to legitimate himself. So he marries Mary Amney, who was essentially
a Hasmonean princess was the daughter of the last king. Right. So he's like, so see, I'm
kind of Hasmoneish. And then he's going to be killing every male Hasmonean he could find.
And then when he killed all the male Hasmonean's, yes. Now I control the bloodlines.
Yes.
That's what does.
That's so he can produce.
the quiz edge. How do I correct? Yeah. So and then appropriately enough, he dies by being eaten
by worms. So good. Hey, he didn't he didn't walk without rhythm. That's the problem. So, uh,
and the the other major thing he does to try to make a name for himself and establish himself is
huge building projects. The most famous one of these that's discussed, the detestive is his massive
expansion of the temple complex.
It took place over decades.
like including after his death in one BC.
So he did do that.
But there are other building projects.
Palace is fortresses, towers, other things all over
what was Judea, right?
And even up toward Galilee that he built
or at least got started during his reign.
And people dig his stuff.
It's kind of a blend of Roman and Near Eastern
architecture instead. But any.
Anyway, didn't get him very far. He's eaten by worms. He dies. The Romans were dissatisfied
with him. So they split up even the little bit of authority that he had four ways among
four of his sons, calling it the tetrarchi. Each of them was called a tetrarke, a ruler
of a fourth. And then the last of the tetrarcs got taken out at the end of the Jewish revolt.
So this last
until the 60s AD, right? 60 years of the tetraarchae with less and less power and authority and influence.
So that all kinds of Peters out, all kind of Peters out. But the lasting legacy of the Hasmonians
and is carried on by the Sadducees, this Hasmonian ideology and carried on by the zealots.
Is this idea where we talked about the Pharisees on the one hand?
We're following through on where God is going to intervene.
The Messiah is going to come.
God is going to set things right.
He's going to remove the curse from us.
He's going to restore Israel.
He's going to do all of these things, right?
That has only an ideology on the other hand is we need to go and take it, right?
They wanted to reconquesta.
We need to go and retake Samaria, retake Galilee and reunite them by force, military, right?
of king and
priest cool with us. We need to, uh, we're looking for a someone to lead a
political revolt, another revolt to have a political and military victory over
the Romans and reestablish an independent Judea. This is what is believed by
all these would be messiahs that we see popping up in the New Testament, the New
Testament period and then after even after the Barcoque Veribault revolt, right?
These are all would be Messiah's and the
issue is what the way we decide whether this person was the Messiah or not from the
Hasmonian ideology perspective is, are they successful?
Yeah.
Right.
Oh, the Romans killed him.
Oh, well, that must have not been the Messiah.
Right.
Which is, which is, which is mean to take a shot.
Yeah, think about that though, right?
Especially in terms of the gospels when they're like, hey, when it's clear that Jesus is
talking about himself getting crucified eventually. They're like...
Um, yeah, the Messiah is supposed to stay forever. He's not going to get crucified by the
comments. Right. We've seen that before. Right. So, and so this is so, so these are the two
real competing ideologies among the zealots and in its different way among the Sadducees,
slightly different, right? And a lot of the common people you have this has voting ideology of
If we are going to do this ourselves, we're going to take it, we're going to take it by force.
Right and violence and we're gonna reestablish
Right this kingdom and that's how
The promises to Abraham that's how these prophecies will be fulfilled and the Pharisees on the other side saying no our job is to keep Torah
Right until that day and be faithful until that day when God acts and intervenes
Right and may that happen soon
Okay. Yeah, it's not just rabbinic Judaism that comes out of herastasm
Christianity comes out of Pharisees.
Yes, it represents this prophetic response to people who want to who think that the kingdom
is of this world.
Yeah.
Like, my kingdom is not of this world.
It's a very fair, sick thing to say.
Yeah.
The, the, and the Hasmodian ideology blossoms into full flower in the Jewish revolts of
the first century.
Which of course are a disaster.
Yeah.
I see the leg.
Yeah, yeah, so the temples destroyed, Jerusalem's destroyed, the the Romans, the Judy eyes, right?
Judea, make it, Palestinian, right? And, and, and remove everything. And yeah, the Pharisees are
essentially the position of saying, told you so. Right. But they're the ones who are prepared to
deal with that. Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah. It's tragic. Is it still all what?
because they're already separate enough.
They already have the synagogue structures to keep going without it.
They were never wedded to it, right?
And they could continue keeping Torah waiting for the Messiah, right?
To intervene and do these things.
They're set up and ready to do that.
But as I just mentioned, and as we're going to get into it, act three, there's another
group spun out of fairsake Judaism that's gonna say hey guys
the Messiah did come and did do all those things you're waiting for and he's
Jesus of Nazareth. Well I'm not bombshell. We're gonna go ahead and take our second
break and we'll be right back. Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Steven DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of
of spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF radio.
Perhaps you are a seeker exploring the abundance of the Orthodox faith, or maybe you're
a young mother wanting to share the fullness of Orthodoxy with your children and family,
or perhaps you are single trying to find shelter from unclean images or words, or an empty
Nester, wanting to fill your time with edifying thoughts, prayers, discussions, and
content or maybe you feel alone and just want to find solace and comfort.
Regardless of your own unique circumstances, ancient faith radio is here to help with your
Orthodox journey.
Please consider partnering with us by becoming a monthly recurring donor so that we can
continue our mission to spread the Orthodox faith and help support the spiritual lives of
the already faithful.
Any consistent donation larger small will enable us to focus on our mission unabated.
Visit www.AncientFake.com slash support.
Starter monthly donations today. All gifts are tax deductible and greatly
appreciated. Thank you.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and
Father Stephen DeYoung. If you have a question call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Welcome back.
By the way, you should know, Father, that...
Your friend Jacob has shown up in the chat and says that he he talked you for five hours last night and he's looking for more
Well, there's at least a couple more here where that came here. We go anyway me being where that came from
Yes, yes, so well, we're back. It's the third half of the third episode of this three episode arc
history of Israel here in Lord of Spirits podcast and
We just left off with the failure of the Hasmoneans
they decided to be super political and combine the priesthood and the kingship and that
didn't go well.
And then you get her and now we're going to move on to my friend Jacob's favorite part,
St. Paul.
There we go.
All right.
So yes, yes.
I mean, we had a caller earlier.
She, you know, how do we, how do you read St. Paul?
Especially if you're used to, if you've been all Calvinized in your brain, you know,
don't do it.
Not once.
It's right.
That's right. So okay, so what is what is what is the Israel that St. Paul is talking about like what is that executive mean?
Yeah, so
Will Bob no no collars
Well
We've kind of gone long and so I made an executive decision
To tell I told Mike to just flip off the phones so I know anyway. No
Oh well, I will soldier on. Sorry everybody. Despite the weakness of my support. Yes.
So yeah, so
One of the so obviously
You know, we're not now at this point in the evening going to be going through here's why Jesus is the Messiah, right?
that's a few episodes of itself.
And we've already had that conversation.
There are a few, go back to our episode.
on Messiah, other things you talked about the past.
We're going to focus here this third half because again, this series is about the history
of Israel and Judah and Judea.
But so one important part of what the Messiah was expected to do was restore Israel.
part of what he's going to do. So as we mentioned at the end of the last half, Christianity
fundamentally at its origins is a movement within Pharisee Judaism that says that Jesus
of Nazareth is the Messiah, meaning that he has done these things. So that raises the
question, how did, if you're saying he did, how did
Jesus of Nazareth, restore Israel. And the reason why I mentioned St. Paul in particular is
this is a particular concert of St. Paul's especially in Romans. And so he's going to present
right, an argument that that is what Christ has done. And we're going to kind of walk through that
here now in this third half. But to get to that we have to start with
the contours of what that expectation looked like from the Hebrew Bible.
So what are the, in many cases from the prophets, right? We're also going to talk about a
couple of Psalms, but where is this expectation of the restoration of Israel come from and how is
it talked about in terms of that expectation? And then St. Paul is going to come back to that and
and talk about
how Jesus as the Messiah fulfills it. So we have to start with one of the primary ways that
the Hebrew Scriptures talk about Israel is that Israel is God's portion or his inheritance,
depending on how it's translated. And this is, I've got, if you really want it,
it. You know, a list of like 37 different places. Yeah, I'm just
that language is
Yeah, just do a word search on it's all art and so portion. Yeah, you can see all that stuff. Yeah, it's there. It's everywhere, right?
But there are also right so there are also some texts. We're going to talk about a couple from the Psalms. This isn't all of them, but this is a couple of them.
that use that word inheritance in a way that goes beyond just to the people of Israel.
Yeah, like, you know, this Psalm 82.
slash 81 if you're reading the Greek version, you know, the one that begins God stood up in the council the gods, et cetera.
Um, and then it ends with the verse the last verse, a rhizogod and judged out of the earth for the thou shalt inherit all the nations inherit all the nations.
Right. Well, from all the nation, from all the nations. Yes. Yeah. Right. So not only is Israel his inheritance, but he has an inheritance from all of the nations.
Right.
Another place that talks about this kind of idea is in Psalm 87.
And this is verses one through six.
Yeah.
So listen to this one.
On the Holy Mount stands the city he founded.
The Lord loves the gates of Zion more than all the dwellings of Jacob.
Glorious things of you are spoken of, city of God.
Among those who know me, I mentioned Rahab and Babylon.
Behold, Philistia and Tyre with Kush.
This one was b-
there they say and of Zion it shall be said this one and that one were born in her for the most
high himself will establish her the Lord records as he registers the peoples this one was born there
so I mean this is people who are from these other nations the Philistines, Tyrion's,
Kushites and they're being reckoned along with with Zion. Right. Right. And this is not describing
Oh, there's gonna be a whole bunch
of people from the 70 nations who are going to convert to
UNASEMOS. We're going to go get circumcised and start keeping
Torah and become Jews. It doesn't say that and it wasn't
interpreted that way in the second temple period because
there weren't Jewish people going around trying to get Gentiles
to convert. Right? It didn't become Jewish. They did not want
that. They were not trying to do that. There was no call to do
that. They didn't read this as a call to do that. Right? But
This is talking.
about, when the time comes that God intervenes, his inheritance is Israel, but is also going
to include some people who are maybe properly speaking Israelites, right, from all the nations.
And it's all made E7. Those are even particular nations who were enemies of Israel. Babylon,
Philistia, Tyre, right? These are enemy nations. Yeah. Right. Nonetheless, right? God has an inheritance there.
Okay. So we have that piece. We also have a piece in terms of the expectation,
the restoration of Israel in the prophets where they're going to talk about Israel being restored.
And this first text we're going to read is what is probably familiar to you.
And if you're an Orthodox Christian, you probably heard it a few weeks ago.
Yes, because it's Reddit Pascar and I
So there's a sad tendency with the old test
to it readings in the services, right?
Where, you know, at like at the offene
and at the great blessing of the waters,
we have all these readings for the old test to it
and it's like, oh, well, they're reading that
because it involves water.
Yeah, just put all the water stuff.
Yeah.
I mean, that's not a true,
but that's at a very shallow level of discourse, right?
The water is deeper as well.
those readings to the feast, the just water. Okay. Yeah. Yeah. So yes, this text we're about
to read talks about something dead coming back to life and we're celebrating the resurrection
at Pascha. But true, but that's a very low level, right? Because the passage of a battery
at Ezekiel chapter 37 verses 1 through 14, this isn't just a question of, oh, hey, we need
to get the surviving.
Judy is a Judahites. We need to get them all back in one place. That's not the restoration of Israel. Right
Israel as it was the twelfth tribe. It is dead by the time of Zikil
The northern kingdom was gone
Yeah, and it's it Judas at exile and it's interesting. I'm dead
You know that that this passage also gets paired in the same services
with a lot of stuff related to Exodus as well.
Yes, so you're getting like this is this is Israel Constitution stuff here. Yeah. Anyway, okay
I'll read it. So people didn't even restored this is how it's talked about. Yeah, this is how so this is from
Ezekiel chapter 37 starting with verse one the hand of the Lord was upon me and he brought me out in the
Spirit of the Lord and set me down in middle of the valley it was full of bones and he led me around
among them and behold there are very many on the surface of the valley and behold they were very dry and
and he said to me
Some of men can these bones live.
And they answered, oh Lord God, you know.
Then he said to me, prophesy over these bones
and say to them, oh, dry bones, hear the word of the Lord.
Thus says the Lord God to these bones,
behold, I will cause breath to enter you
and you shall live.
And I will lay sinews upon you and you will,
and will cause flesh to come upon you
and cover you with skin and put breath in you
and you shall live and you shall know that I am the Lord.
So I prophesied as I was commanded.
And as I prophesied,
There was a-
sound to behold a rattling and the bones came together, bone to its bone. And I looked
and behold there were sinews on them and flesh had come upon them and skin had covered
them, but there was no breath in them. Then he said to me, prophesied to the breath,
prophesied some of man and say to the breath, thus says the Lord God, come from the four
winds, oh breath, and breathe on these slain that they may live. So I prophesied as he
commanded me, and the breath came into them and they lived and stood on their feet and
exceeding the great
army. Then he said to me, Son of Man, these bones are the whole house of Israel. Behold,
they say our bones are dried up and our hope is lost. We are indeed cut off. Therefore,
prophesy and say to them, thus says the Lord God, behold, I will open your graves and
raise you from your graves, O my people. And I will bring you into the land of Israel.
And you shall know that I am the Lord where I open your graves and raise you from your
the graves of my people, and I will put my spirit within you and you shall live.
I will place you in your own land, then you shall know that I am the Lord.
I have spoken and I will do it to cleanse the Lord."
So this is what it has to be resurrected from the debt.
Yeah.
Okay.
That's what needs to happen for Israel to be restored.
There needs to be a resurrection.
already to tip the hat of kind of where this is going.
Read Romans, the resurrection of Jesus for St. Paul is the beginning of the resurrection of Israel.
Yeah. But we need to go a little further. So this is what needs to happen.
But again, importantly, according to the prophets, and we're going to read a couple of things
from Jeremiah now. And in those
couple of things from Jeremiah.
It's going to be made very clear prophetically that this again isn't just about Judah.
This isn't just about those surviving Judahites being brought out of exile or all collected
in one place again, or even having a king again and having a high priest again and having
a temple again.
It's not about that, right?
It goes beyond that, right, that the northern kingdom also has to be and is going to be
restored.
Yeah.
Okay, so this is from Jeremiah chapter 31 according to the Hebrew numbering and 38 in the Greek numbering.
The Lord appeared to him from far away.
I have loved you with an everlasting love.
Therefore I have continued my faithfulness to you.
Again, I will build you and you shall be built, O Virgin Israel.
Again, you shall adore yourself with tambourines and shall go forth in the dance of the Mary makers.
Again, you shall plant vineyards on the mountains of Samaria.
The planters show plant until enjoy the fruit.
for there shall be a day when Watchman will call in the hill country of Ephraim,
arise and let us go up to Zion to the Lord our God. Remember everybody, Ephraim is, in many cases,
Old Testament shorthand for the Northern Kingdom. The King's...
And Samaria is the capital of the Northern... Samaria is the capital. And notice here, notice here,
how that concludes. It might not strike you immediately, but notice the watchman call out.
for the Ephraimites, for this restored northern kingdom to go to Zion, to Jerusalem, to the temple
to worship God. That never happened in the northern kingdom. We went through that history. Jeroboam
son of Nabat, first thing he did in establishing the northern kingdom, golden calves at Bethel and Dan,
worship there do not go back to the temple. So it's not just that
Hey, we're going to get the band back together. Hey, the physical biological people are going
to be gathered back together. It's going to be different this time. Yeah, right. That
ideal of the Torah that they were supposed to be, that's what they're going to become.
Even the northern kingdom folks, right? Yeah. Jeremiah also says,
Jeremiah also says this is Jeremiah this is chapter 50 in the the Hebrew text
27 in the Greek text, yet Greek and Hebrew Jeremiah are not in the same order.
In those days and in that time declares the Lord the people of Israel and the people of Judah.
Notice that Israel and Judah shall come together weeping as they come and they shall seek the Lord their God.
They shall ask the way to Zion with faces turned toward it saying, come let us join ourselves to the Lord in an everlasting covenant that will never be forgotten.
So you have du-covenant, right?
which is renewed covenant, language, right?
Israel and Judah can't come together
if they're the same people person, right?
It's the same group, right?
Yeah.
Let's talk about Israel like Northern Kingdom
and Judah like Southern Kingdom.
Right, so very clearly this includes both.
And now we're going to go.
We read Ezekiel, the dry bones passage
is Ezekiel 37, 1 through 14.
But we're not going to continue in verse 15.
Yes, yes. The word of the Lord came to me. Son of man take a stick and write on it for Judah
and the people of Israel associated with them. Then take another stick and write on it for Joseph,
the stick of Ephraim and all the house of Israel associated with him and join them one to another
into one stick that they may become one in your hand. And when your people say to you, will you not
tell us what you mean by these.
Say to them, thus says the
Lord God, behold, I'm about to take the stick of Joseph that is in the hand of Ephraim,
and the tribes of Israel associated with him.
And I will join with it the stick of Judah and make them one stick that they may be one
in my hand.
When the sticks on which you write are in your hand before your eyes, then say to them,
thus says the Lord God, behold, I will take the people of Israel from among the nations
among which they have gone, and will gather them from all around
and bring them to their own land.
And I will make them one nation in the land on the mountains of Israel, and one king shall
be king over them all, and they shall be no longer two nations and no longer divided into
two kingdoms.
They shall not defile themselves anymore with their idols and their detestable things or
with any of their transgressions.
But I will save them from all the backslideings in which they have sinned and will cleanse them,
and they shall be my people, and I will be their God.
My servant David, so we king over them, and they sell all-
have one shepherd. They shall walk in my rules and be careful to obey my statutes.
All right. So again, Taurus not just going to be an ideal that strive for
that order is going to be achieved and notice Israel, the northern kingdom, they're going to come
back from the nations into which they were dispersed. That can't be literal.
Right.
Because the literal people who were sent into a Syria are dead at the Dibasee heels saying
this.
Right.
And then their descendants have assimilated.
Yes.
Like they're just, they're not who they are anymore.
So we're putting the pieces out here.
Okay.
So when we come to St. Paul talking about this, which is in Romans chapters 9 through 11,
Calvinists all over are getting excited.
You're going to be disappointed.
When were you think it's going?
Quite the opposite
Sorry Calvinist
Right in order to understand what St Paul is gonna do so St Paul a lot of what he's talking about especially chapters 10 and 11 is he's talking about the Northern Kingdom
And the way he's gotten there is is in Romans 9 through 11 St Paul is addressing the fact that
Look even looking around at that time
You're saying Jesus of Nazareth is the Messiah, right? He's the Messiah, he's the King of the Jews, right?
And I look around, I've seen a lot of Jews who don't think he's the Messiah, right?
Who don't accept that he's the Messiah. So what's up with that? Right? If he's the Messiah, why have it all
all the Jewish people recognize him as the Messiah? Why only some of you? And now you've got all these
people who aren't even Jews saying is the Messiah. Right? What's up with this
This is what he's answering.
And so he starts out in Romans 9 talking about Jacob and Esau, Isaac and Ishmael, saying,
hey, look, it was never everybody descended from Abraham.
Right?
It was never everybody was never about just like everyone who's literally Abraham's seed.
There were always some, right, and then some others.
Right?
And he follows that through to talk about faithful remnant.
remnant but man like have you have you read the Hebrew Bible right like the masses the vast
majority of the Israelites were not faithful people yeah we're not keeping the chart there's
always a faithful remnant who were but there's this big body right so that's sort of Saint Paul's
first argument is like if you are familiar with the Jewish scriptures you know that that isn't a
a weird situation, right? There would be a lot of
of Jewish people who would not accept the Messiah when he comes. That's not totally unprecedented.
And now he kind of goes into this side question of, well, yeah, but what's going on with that?
Yeah. Right? Like, why does God bring these 12 tribes out of Egypt, right? And go through all this.
and a lot of horses of light.
to each of these tribes, what he knows, right?
We talked about last time what a short period of time
it was that they existed as Israel.
And now they're just gone.
Like, what was the point of all that?
Right? Like, why doesn't God just redeem
and bless the faithful remnant?
Yeah.
Right? Like the ones he knows very well.
What's going on with this?
And so St. Paul is going to appeal to another
is set up.
ideas from the Old Testament. But in order to understand what St. Paul is doing, we have to read
first this another passage from Jeremiah, another text from the Hebrew scriptures that St. Paul
is referencing. That's in the background of what St. Paul says. Because if say you're a Calvinist
and you don't read Jeremiah, when you're reading this, you'll get confused.
Right. Take it.
about a context. Remember the Bible is hypertextual. Yes. Everything can be...
everything. Okay so this is from Jeremiah chapter 18 starting with verse 1. The word that came to
Jeremiah from the Lord arise and go down to the potter's house and there I will let you hear my
words. So I went down to the potter's house and there he was working at his wheel. And the vessel he
was making of clay was spoiled in the potter's hand and he reworked it into another vessel as it
seemed good to the potter to do. Then the word of the Lord came to me, oh house of Israel. Can I not
do with you as this potter has done to clear the Lord, behold, like the clay in the potter's
hand, so are you in my hand, O house of Israel.
If at any time I declare something concerning a nation or a kingdom that I will pluck up
and break down and destroy it, and if that nation concerning which I have spoken turns
from its evil, I will relent of the disaster that I intended to do it.
And if at any time I declare concerning a nation or a kingdom that I will build and plant it,
If it does evil in my sight, not listening to my voice...
then I will relent to the good that I had intended to do it.
Now, therefore, say to the men of Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem,
thus says the Lord, behold, I am shaping disaster against you and devising a plan against you.
Return everyone from his evil way and amend your ways and your deeds,
but they say that is in vain.
We will follow our own plans and will everyone act according to the stubbornness of his evil heart.
Yeah, I mean, it's so from this, it's clear that what God is saying to Jeremiah is.
And this is the where the whole Potter image comes from that as you were about to talk about the St. Paul uses that if
If the Potter has plans for God, God says it basically if I have if I'm gonna punish some some nation and
They turn from their evil. I won't punish them
If I'm gonna bless a nation and they turn to evil then I will not bless them right it's really dependent on what the nation does
Right, and that these are nations right the potters vessels here are nations right and he makes them for a purpose and he has an intent with them right but that intent is not
like a
Forgon conclusion
Right, so if he makes a nation with good intent toward it, but they turn to evil minute
right and they're wicked and he intends to destroy it but they repent.
Right. Yeah.
This is this is not predestination. No, no, it is the opposite of predestination. God is gonna do whatever he wants no matter what they do. Right. Okay. So
within the argument Romans say Paul's gonna say Northern Kingdom of Israel is made by God for a purpose
for a purpose.
And in the latter part of
of Romans 9, he's going to start getting into the idea of what that purpose was, for which
the northern kingdom and those tribes were brought out of Egypt and were created.
Yeah. So now keeping in mind, what we just heard from Jeremiah, yes, Romans 9, starting
with verse 20, but who are you, oh man, and so back back to God? Well, what is molded,
say to its molder, why have you made me like this? Has the potter no right over the clay
to make out of the same lump one vest.
for honorable use and another for dishonorable use. What if God, Desiring to show His wrath and to
make known as power, has endured with much patience, vessels of wrath prepared for destruction,
in order to make known the riches of His glory for vessels of mercy, which He's prepared beforehand
for glory, even us whom He has called, not from the Jews only, but also from the Gentiles.
Yes, notable. This is all a question. Is it not possible? Can God do what He wants?
Yeah, right. But
Notice, he's using the same language for Jeremiah, right?
He has this vessel prepared for glory, right?
And he says, right, in Jeremiah, he talks about the tradition that he will build and
plant, right?
Yeah.
So he has the same thing, right?
So Prince Rewr's in view.
Now notice he says he talks about bearing with those vessels.
prefer for wrath, meaning they're not repenting, right? But he is patient with them.
Why is he? How is he patient with them? If he just, if he's just waiting for the right time
to destroy them, right? If he's just saying, well, I don't have to destroy them immediately.
I could wait and destroy them later if it fits my plan. That's not being patient with them.
Right?
Being patient with them means he's giving them a...
opportunity an opportunity to repent. Yeah, he's given him a chance which is weirdly consistent
with how God acts throughout the whole scriptures. Right. It's strangely. Right. So he's giving
them a chance to repent. Okay. Say Paul's talking about the northern kingdom here. God created
them, gave them this existence and bore with them for a couple hundred years, giving them
a chance to repent.
other than they didn't. But even within that, within his destruction of them, St. Paul
is saying, God is going to use that destruction. He's going to use the judgment that they
brought upon themselves with their sin. He's going to use that to do something good for
someone else who is faithful. And that someone else who is faithful is not going to be just
the Jews, but it's going to include some people from the nations. Yeah. This is laying the
groundwork for the big analogy that St. Paul is going to use in chapter 11 of the olive tree.
Okay. But before we launch into that, okay, okay, okay. I guess why do we mean to the Calvinists
one last time? I mean, what do you mean one last time this evening? Well, I was going to say,
You know it's gonna happen again.
What St. Paul is talking about here is not double predestination.
He's talking Jeremiah here, people, which teaches the exact opposite.
The God will turn from his intent, good or bad, based on repentance or lack of repentance
of wickedness and sin.
So, St. Paul is not teaching the opposite of Jeremiah.
He's teaching the same thing Jeremiah is teaching. He's talking about nations, not about individuals.
Okay. Now, the olive tree. All right, the olive tree.
Romans 11, starting with verse 17. But if some of the branches were broken off,
and you, although a wild olive shoot, were grafted in among the others and now share in the
the nourishing root of the olive tree, do not be arrogant toward the branches.
If you are, remember it is not you who support the root, but the root that supports you.
Then you will say, branches were broken off so that I might be grafted in.
That is true.
They were broken off because of their unbelief, but you stand fast through faith.
So do not become proud, but fear.
For if God did not spare the natural branches, neither will He spare you.
Note then the kindness and the severity of God, severity toward those who have fallen,
God's kindness to you provided you continue in His kind.
is, otherwise you too will be cut off. And even they, if they do not continue in their
unbelief, will be grafted in, forgot as the power to graft them in again. But if you were
cut off from what is by nature, a wild olive tree and grafted, contrary to nature, into a cultivated
olive tree, how much more will these the natural branches be grafted back into their own olive tree?
Lest you be wise in your own sight, I do not want you to be unaware of the Smithtree brothers. A
a partial hardening has come upon Israel until the f***.
fullness of the Gentiles has come in. And in this way, all Israel will be saved. As it is written,
the deliverer will come from Zion. He will banish ungodliness from Jacob. And this will be my covenant
with them when I take away their sins." Okay, so a few things about this metaphor that we need to
observe. First of all, sorry dispensationalists there's only one olive tree.
Not to. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. It doesn't say, well, God took a break from dealing with that first
all of tree. He'll get back to it. But he planted this second one. Yeah. No.
There's one one one all of three. Also, those of you who
want to say like old covenant dead and gone, Israel cut off church new thing, right? Church
has replaced Israel. There's only one tree. God doesn't uproot the original tree and
plan a new one. Yeah, that he hopes will grow better. That's not the analogy, right?
That doesn't work, okay? What this is saying is there were branches on that tree.
We're going to Abraham. This tree is Israel, right? It's very clear. He says the tree's Israel, okay?
Israel is the Old Testament and all through its history, branches were broken off. Why were they
broken off? Because they were unfaithful. Yeah, that's unfaithful to God. Here, he says this.
Yes, that's why they're ugly.
all through history. And there's a possibility that they that the unfaithful branch which gets which
gets broken off can be put back in if they repent and turn back to God and and become faithful,
they'll get grafted right back in. So it's not permanent. Right. But all throughout history,
it's happened. Right. Read the revival. Right. That that big swaths. Right. Have been cut off for
their faithfulness. But in God's prominence, right, and in his mercy.
All of those branches that were cut off by their own faithlessness, by their own
faithlessness, Calvinists. That's what he says here. Not God's predetermination.
They were cut off, leave space for these wild branches to be grafted in.
Okay, that's part of the providence.
Now there's this space to be filled by the full
of the Gentiles, fullness of the nations.
Okay.
Yeah, which we'll get into that more in a second.
Yeah, I was gonna say that's a callback right there.
Yeah, we'll get back to that in a second.
Okay.
We've got a couple more things to notice here.
Number two, or three or whatever we're on.
Right.
To notice, notice the wild olive branches do not become something other than wild olive
branches.
Yeah.
by nature wild olive branches.
They are by nature wild all of branches and they stay wild all of branches.
Right? So these people from the nations who are being grafted in do not become Jewish.
They do not get circumcised. They do not start following you to Ismos. They remain branches from
whatever tree they came from, but now they're grafted in meaning what? Meaning they're still who they
They are. They're still Greeks.
partheid's Persians, Americans, Dutch people, Lithuanians, right? But they're
driving their life and their nourishment from this tree that is Israel, right? From
its root, which is Abraham and his faithfulness, right? That's why he says,
the tree supports you, you don't support the tree to those people, right? And the
the base of the tree.
Where that life is coming up and through are the natural branches, right?
That faithful remnant into which these wild branches are being grafted.
Okay.
And so the fullness, right, the fullness of the Gentiles, there's another place where
this exact phrase is used in the scriptures.
Yeah, in Genesis.
Testament of Jacob.
Well, it's before the Testament of Jacob.
I'm sorry, yeah, yeah.
With Joseph.
Joseph, yeah, yeah, sorry, Joseph.
Yeah.
Yeah, so Genesis 49 is technically the testament of Jacob.
So that's where Jacob slash the person Israel
is blessing his sons on his deathbed.
In Genesis 48, before that, Joseph brings his two sons,
but that's...
and Ephraim to be blessed, Ephraim is actually the younger son to Jacob to be blessed. And Jacob
crosses his hands and uses his right hand to bless Ephraim even though he's the younger because
by that point, if you've been reading Genesis at all, you get the point that it's often the younger
son who's considered the first born. But
and so Ephraim receives this blessing and part of that blessing is that his descendants will become
the fullness of the fullness.
of the Gentiles, the fullness of the nations. Right. And so what
say Paul is saying by using that phrase is he saying the the
people of the northern kingdom who were cut off for their
faithlessness. We're scattered like seed. Remember what he said,
what say Paul says it out of the place. The seed falls into the
the ground it must die.
So they were the king of those tribes die, but they're scattered like seed out there among the nations.
And then centuries later, now that Jesus has come as the Messiah, St. Paul is saying, now's the harvest time.
If you're paying attention, Jesus already said that.
Hmm.
If you are paying attention on Sunday and you go to North of Doc's church, you heard Jesus say that about the Samaritans.
Yeah, he was in Samaria and he said to disciples, the fields are ripe for the harvest. We need workers for the harvest.
Yeah, so it's this idea that this really ancient, I mean, by this point, really ancient prophecy, you know, about Ephraim is fulfilled in the nations getting grafted in.
Right.
and they get the questions sort of a rue from right who are becoming faithful to God in the Messiah in Jesus right are being
grafted in and now drawing their life from the root that is the faithful remnant of Israel right and we can part of the tree and so once the fullness of
Once all of those have come in, right?
And all of the natural born people, right?
The Jews.
Let's just say the...
Jews have had an opportunity to repent and be grafted back in if they've been cut off
or remain and grow if they never were cut off.
They've remained faithful.
And once all of those are grafted in who are going to be grafted in, then this one whole
tree, which Saint Paul calls in Romans 11, verse 25, all Israel will be saved.
Then the tree will be complete.
Then Israel will be restored.
this idea?
We've seen this idea in other places like in our series where we've been talking about
Second Temple Jewish literature when we talked about the testaments of the 12 patriarchs.
We talked about the testament of Ephraim and we talked about the testament of Levi and
about how they say straight out that through Joseph, right, through Ephraim, the Mesopotamians,
the Babylonians, right, it names all of these nations and aminations, will receive an inheritance
with Israel.
So this isn't just something St. Paul's making up.
This isn't just a cope, right?
This isn't just an ad hoc thing he's throwing together to try to explain how Jesus can be the Messiah when he didn't do Messiah things.
Right?
This is a way in which other people in the second temple Jewish period, other Jewish people were interpreting their scriptures to say
This makes sense in terms of how God can fulfill restoring the Northern.
kingdom. The Northern Kingdom dying and being scattered as seed and the fruit of that seed
now coming back to God and being grafted in to the faithful remnant that remains. And so,
at the end of this, we have to disambiguate some categories. So when the New Testament
Talks about Israel.
that is not synonymous with Judea or the Judeans. It includes Judea and the Judeans.
But Israel, in terms of this tree, it goes beyond that. There are some other people from the
perspective of the New Testament, starting with the Samaritans, who are also able to, through their
faithfulness to the God of Israel through his Messiah.
going to be able to receive an inheritance with Israel. So it is not just synonymous. Israel
is not synonymous in the New Testament for the New Testament writers with those who practice
Uday's most. Again, they're included, right, or those who practice Judaism as it's transliterated,
right they're included, they're that root, they're the natural
raise it right but there are all
also these who are grafted in who find inner herds of Israel.
So Israel, for the respective of St. Paul and New Testament writers, we're talking about
all Israel.
We're talking about the whole tree, which includes Judah, Slash, Judea, Slash, the
practiceers of Judaism, the keepers of the Torah, right, and the fullness of the nations
who are grafted in, who restore the northern cave.
And so, within...
And this is, we're covered in our conclusion.
We've been critiquing a lot these episodes,
dispensationalism, but we've also critiqued here,
supersessionism.
Right?
Again, it's not the old tree gets thrown in a fire
and God plants a new one.
Right?
St. Tree.
Bet that the Udae, right?
The Jews still have a central role.
They're still distinct.
Right?
Just as everyone who's grafted in remains distinct, remains Greek or Russian or Dutch or Polish or whatever.
They remain distinct, right?
But the Jews still have a special central role because salvation is from the Jews.
Christ says that, right? Christ himself, Jewish.
He's the Jewish Messiah, right? This all comes. That's the root.
Right that supports the branches the branches
don't support that. But they are not the whole. They're not the whole thing. There are these
others who are grafted in and included. That is not, when I say that, I'm not saying that
to counter Jewish claims. I'm mostly countering bad Christian claims. Because, for example,
would say Paul asks in Galatians.
is God the God of the Jews only and not also the God of the nations. He's expecting all the Jewish
people he's talking to to be like, well, no, of course, he's also the God of the nations.
Right? He doesn't think that his other Jewish ideologues think he's only the God of the Jews.
Right? He doesn't think that. Right? He's expecting them to agree. That's why he's making that argument.
Right.
it. And so.
One of the big problems with the dispensational paradigm is that it assumes that in the same way that a lot of folks we had a color about this want to limit salvation to Christians or the possibility of salvation to Christians we should say.
Conversely, there's a lot of Christians who want to act like only Jewish people were saved
in the Old Testament, right, or before Jesus.
And then sort of now after Jesus now people who aren't Jewish can find salvation like
Read the Bible
Right, that's not the case. That was never the case
That's what we were talking about in the first episode especially
It was never the case that it was just the Jewish people who were in God's plan
So what St Paul is saying here is not that wild and out there
From the perspective of the Hebrew scriptures from the perspective of second-table Judaism
I don't even think it's out there for the
perspective of rabbinic Judaism later, depending on where you're at in it.
Right. If you could accept that that's what St. Paul's actually saying, I don't think it's that far out.
Right. Obviously, a lot of, you know, any Jewish person who doesn't agree that Jesus is the Messiah
is going to disagree with St. Paul, but disagreeing and thinking he's wrong is different than saying,
this is totally out of line with Jewish thought. Those are two different questions.
And so...
Here to put a pin on it at the conclusion of our third episode in this history of Israel,
I would say thus based on what St. Paul has told us that the rest of the history of Israel
is actually kind of church history.
And so this isn't a church history podcast.
So you should all email Gary Cyril Jenkins and ask him to do a series continuing
what we've started here. He's going to have to start listening to the show again.
Yeah, and threatening with things if he won't do it.
Yeah. Yeah. Well, I think that it's hard to say one big takeaway from all three of these
episodes. I mean, now how long will we spend talking about this? Maybe 10 hours or so?
in addition to the other things we've said about Israel
for the last almost five years now,
of this podcast.
But I think that for me, the biggest takeaway is,
and I've said this before, but I'm gonna say it again,
I guess, and maybe in a way this time,
that the, as you said, father,
The new covenant is really the
renewed covenant.
You know, it's not a second covenant.
It's not a separate thing.
It is the same covenant from God, from the beginning.
It's not Plan B.
You know, it's renewed.
And in fact, what's shown is how all of these seeds
that are planted throughout the Old Testament
come to flower in the New Testament.
So it's not some some radical new thing.
You know, that like for instance that that Ephraim will be the fullness of the nations
Right, I mean that goes back all the way back to
To the 12 tribes the not just the 12 tribes the 12 men, you know the 12 patriarchs who headed up those tribes
Who are the fathers of the stripes? I mean that's that's the beginning that's that's even pre-Israel at Quai Israel
right
And so
One of the
problems of, I think, one of the great problems of Christians in the modern period, whether orthodox,
or Protestants, or Catholics, or whatever else, is what is the relationship of the Christian
to the Old Testament? I think that's one of the great problems of our time. And I think that the
source of a lot of that, frankly, is stuff that the Reformation got wrong.
It's got it wrong.
And as a result, then, there's all these conflicted relationships with the Old Testament.
And it plays out in lots of different ways.
We've of course criticized dispensationalism over and over and over again throughout this
series.
And of course, Calvinism, a number of times as well.
But I'll say this, like from within the Orthodox community, we do have a problem.
It's not a problem with orthodox cre-
Christianity. It's not a problem with the Orthodox tradition. It's a problem of the faithfulness of Orthodox people,
which is that a lot. Maybe I'll even go ahead and say that the average
Orthodox Christian is almost completely clueless about the Old Testament.
And it's not that he doesn't care about his faith. I'm saying even like the faithful ones,
like the ones who want to be serious and so forth. It's not that he doesn't care. It's that he has a wrong relationship with it.
that he's misunderstood what it has to do.
with him as an orthodox Christian.
Right? And so what we've tried to do in this series
is to begin to reconnect us
by showing how the arc of the whole story is our story.
It is our story.
These are our fathers and mothers in the faith.
Whether we have a drop of Semitic blood in us or not.
Right?
You know, if if you're a non-Jewish Christian,
you're one of those wild olive branches
that have been grafted into the natural olive branch,
to the natural olive tree.
You graft it and you receive life as St. Paul says,
from that root.
Right?
It's not a separate tree.
It's not like, oh, that was the Old Testament.
It doesn't matter anymore.
We don't believe that anymore.
I'm sorry.
If you're an orthodox criminal,
you see that stuff, you are acting like some kind of weird Protestant, frankly.
Now, I'm not saying all Protestants are that way. Obviously Protestants take the Old Testament
seriously. They do. They frankly, the average one, at least, this is the way it was when I was
a kid, I don't know if it's the case anymore. But the average one, at least, used to read it a lot
more than the average Orthodox Christian. For sure, I mean, it's to our shame, to our shame.
Right? But because of the distortions of the reformation, the relationship to the
that part of the tradition is distorted,
doctrinally within the Reformation.
For Orthodox Christians, if we're looking on it and saying,
well, you know, that doesn't really apply to us anymore.
Do I really need that?
Whatever, whatever, whatever.
We are not acting in accordance with the Orthodox tradition.
Like, read the writings of the church fathers.
It is very clear that they were super into the Old Testament.
They saw it as mattering a great deal.
A great deal.
That is the language that they speak.
But even set them aside, it is the language of the Apostles speak.
They speak the language of the Old Testament.
That is the language that they speak.
And you're not going to understand, just like we showed some bits from St. Paul today,
you're not going to understand what the Apostles say.
If you don't understand what the language is that they're speaking, you're not.
So it's really, really critical that we reclaim this for each of ourselves.
As I said, it's not the...
Orthodox tradition that needs to reclaim it. It's all there. You know, listen to the church services,
read the church fathers, all these things that are the living tradition of the Orthodox church.
It is very, very present. It is very present. But if I am not present to it, then I have a problem.
Then I have a problem. And you know, it's one of the great missions of the five-year mission of
of this podcast. Could go longer.
who knows five years so far to say to Orthodox people and anybody else who will listen to us,
look, look, look at the scriptures, especially the Old Testament. Look at it deeply, you know,
it's really, it is an adventure, my friends. It is just the most incredible story and it's
all true. It's all true. So
So don't be crypto Marcy Knights.
You know, Marcy and who rejected the Old Testament.
And thus it distorted the New Testament for him.
Don't be that way.
You know, dive in.
It's okay if you don't understand it all.
Just read it.
Just start by reading it.
And you know, listen to, like I love Father Alexis Corey's
Daily Orthodox Scriptures podcast.
Listen to that.
You listen to that podcast every day for a year.
You'll hear the whole Bible.
right? And you keep doing it from year to year to year, you start to really get to know
the scriptures little by little. It's so, so worth it. It's so worth it. We're in such a hurry here
in 2025. We got so many other things to do. But what is life for? Like why are we, why are we doing
all these things to keep ourselves alive? Is it just so we stay alive? Just so we stay comfortable?
or is it for something?
And what it is that the Scriptures unlock for us, that's what it's for.
So that's what I have to say here at the end of this series.
Oh, it was a matter.
Yeah, you can talk if you want, Father.
So our world is full of hasmonians.
And it has been...
for a good century and a half, maybe even two centuries. Lots of examples. Start with controversial
ones. Zionism. And by Zionism, that's not code, by the way. I don't mean quote unquote
the Jews. By Zionism, I mean Zionists. The numerical majority of which are evangelical
Christians, not Jewish in any sense.
So you're dispensationalists.
Or you're Christian nationalists.
I warn you once again out there, you Orthodox folks online who think you want to be Christian
nationalists. The Christian nationalists in the United States don't think you're a Christian.
The first thing they're going to do is burn your icons because they think they're idols.
They destroy our churches, okay.
Christian nationalism, communism, national socialism, right?
On and on.
What all of these ideologies have in common, they all have in common with the hasmonians.
We're going to get God to intervene.
We're going to establish justice.
We're going to make everything right.
We're going to usher in the kingdom, right?
That's what Reich means by the way.
We're going to do this and we're going to do it ourselves.
We're going to do it through our efforts.
And our efforts is always code for violence.
Our efforts is always code for killing a lot of people.
And harming a lot of people.
Victimizing a lot of people.
That's what always happens.
Okay.
Be a Pharisee.
The Pharisees were the good guys.
Doesn't mean they're above critique. Doesn't mean every one of them was a good person.
Right?
But in the face of all that, in the face of all these plans and projects and agendas and
pushes that everyone wants you to get on board with,
everybody wants you to participate in.
All these programs and plans,
Always to generate into file.
You be the person who stands apart from that who follows the scriptures.
It's faithful to Christ in your life and keeps the commandments.
Lives your life according to the way of life that God set out for you.
You do that in the midst of all the turmoil.
Doesn't mean you're going to get a free pass.
So
Pharisees. You'll either end up one of the victims of one of those programs.
But if you do, that's martyrdom.
If that happens to you because you're being faithful to God, there's a reward waiting for you.
That's the answer. The answer is not to start a counter-movement.
The answer is not to do violence back to repay evil with evil.
Rather than trying to overcome evil with good.
I think from tonight in particular, that is the important message.
That spirit of the Hasmoneans is not the Holy Spirit.
That's why there was no spirit of prophecy in the land in those days.
It's a very different spirit.
It's a spirit like all spirits that aren't the Holy Spirit leads men to.
destruction, destroying themselves and others.
Famous quote, what is good?
What does the Lord require of you?
To do justly to love mercy, to accomplish with your God?
So we quoted last time from Deuteronomy
what God has commanded us is not too difficult for us.
It's giving us what we need to do it.
We just need to shift our focus to doing that.
Doing that and waiting for God to act, waiting for Him to intervene, knowing that He will.
And awaiting the glorious appearing of our Lord Jesus Christ.
Now you can go home and go to sleep, Father Andrew.
And you can go play Marvel rivals.
Right?
late into the evening.
Well, with that, that is our show for tonight.
Thank you very much everyone for listening.
If we didn't talk to you tonight,
a lot of we'd like to hear from you.
You can email us, Lordofspiritznames and Feet.com.
You can message us on our Facebook page.
You can leave us a voice mail at SpeakPipe.com,
slash Lordofspiritz.
And if you have basic questions about Orthodox Christianity,
or you need help to find a parish out here in the 3D world,
head over to Orthodoxintro.org.
and join us for our live broadcast on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7 p.m. Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific.
Madness in the winds got something to say. It ripped you apart. We'll always be that way.
If you're on Facebook, you can follow our page. You can join our discussion group.
Leave all those readings and reviews wherever they go and share the show with somebody because
word of mouth is the way. Don't just rely on AI.
I'll probably be sure to go to ancientfaith.com,
stroke support and help make sure we and lots of other,
if our pockets.
and I can't just look back, back again, you want it all,
but it's on the run. The sky will open.
Thank you, Good Night. God bless you. Christ is risen.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits,
with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick
and Father Stephen DeYoung, a listener-supported presentation
of Ancient Faith Radio. And I beheld, and I heard the voice
the voice of many angels round about the throne.
beasts and the elders, and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000 than thousands of
thousands, saying with a loud voice, worthy as the land that was slain to receive power and
riches, and wisdom, and strength, and honor, and glory, and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11-12.
Orthodox Christianity for today's world.
You are listening to ancient faith radio.
Saint Dorothea of Cesaria.
Saint Dorothea was known for her beauty and wisdom even on a young age.
She was filled with great faith and drew the attention of the local ruler, Saperkis.
He has two sisters, Christina and Kalista.